<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The French rogue: or, The life of Monsieur Ragoue de Versailles Containing his parentage; monstrous birth, early rogueries, pleasant and witty pranks, not only in France, but in divers other countries. With the strange and wonderful plots, projects, policies and stratagems, by which he contrived, managed, and brought about his villanies, and escaped many dangers; and more particularly the prank he played with the French king, &amp;c. All very comical and delightful. Done from the original by J.S.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 204 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 101 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84910</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2196C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R226224</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895660</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895660</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153229</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84910)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153229)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2355:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The French rogue: or, The life of Monsieur Ragoue de Versailles Containing his parentage; monstrous birth, early rogueries, pleasant and witty pranks, not only in France, but in divers other countries. With the strange and wonderful plots, projects, policies and stratagems, by which he contrived, managed, and brought about his villanies, and escaped many dangers; and more particularly the prank he played with the French king, &amp;c. All very comical and delightful. Done from the original by J.S.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], iv, [2], 184 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for N. Boddington, at the Golden Ball in Duck-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Frontis. = ill.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B-H¹²  I.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:153229:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153229:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153229:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153229:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153229:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153229:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153229:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153229:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153229:5"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of three scenes from the narrative: the frightening of the schoolmaster with fire and fireworks; the public whipping of two courtesans; and the cheating of the Pope with a fake St Peter's beard</figDesc>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Though young he his old ſchoolmaster out wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>And the fine Miſses with a whiping fitts</l>
                     <l>The Pope He Cheats and proues in all t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> Reſt</l>
                     <l>Rogue who will Rogue french Rogury thriues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153229:5"/>
            <p>THE French Rogue: OR, THE LIFE OF Monſieur <hi>RAGO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E De Verſailles.</hi> CONTAINING His Parentage, Monſtrous Birth, Early Rogueries, Pleaſant and Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Pranks, not only in <hi>France,</hi> but in divers other Countries. With the Strange and Wonderful Plots, Projects, Policies and Stratagems, by which he Contrived, Managed, and Brought about his Villanies, and eſcaped many Dangers; and more particularly the Prank he played with the <hi>French</hi> KING, &amp;c. All very Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical and Delightful.</p>
            <p>Done from the Original by <hi>J. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>N. Boddington,</hi> at the <hi>Golden Ball</hi> in <hi>Duck-lane,</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:153229:6"/>
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:153229:6"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>IN this ſmall Book you will find ſuch delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Entertainment as none of this kind has yet afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; it is dreſſed, the better to pleaſe, in the Modiſh Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of <hi>France,</hi> ſome years ſince ſo greatly in requeſt,
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:153229:7"/> that few Ladies or Sparks found themſelves eaſie, and undone without a Taylor that had croſſed the Water to take a Survey of that Fantaſtical Court, and bring over Models of the Neweſt Bravery in vogue. To be brief, If you are deſirous to divert your ſelf with what may contribute to Mirth, and baniſh Melancholly Thoughts, or dive into the depth of Ingenious
<pb n="iii" facs="tcp:153229:7"/> Roguery, here you may have your Wiſhes anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at a ſmall Expence, in ſo curious and pleaſing a Style of Proſe, interwoven with Poetry, that the like we dare affirm, never came to your Hands. Take it then, as it is, and when you have ſeriouſly peruſed it (but not till then) Judge, and ſpeak as you find, and no doubt you will conclude that you never met with a
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:153229:8"/> better Help to remove a Fit of the Spleen. And ſo paſſing through this little Porch into a fair and large Houſe, I leave you to take its Dimenſions at Leiſure.</p>
            <closer>And remain, <signed>Your very Humble Servant, <hi>J. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:153229:8"/>
            <head>On the Ingenious AUTHOR OF THE <hi>French Rogue,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <lg>
               <l>IN this no Common Rogue you find,</l>
               <l>It is a <hi>French</hi> One, (pray that Notion, mind)</l>
               <l>One who more Cunning than the reſt has been,</l>
               <l>Out-witting all that ever yet were ſeen:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>French</hi> Tricks, you know, are for Invention rare,</l>
               <l>Once coveted like Faſhions, or their Ware.</l>
               <l>No Modes, but French, would pleaſe ſome Years ago,</l>
               <l>So that their Vice became a Faſhion too.</l>
               <l>If a <hi>French Venus</hi> in hot Kindneſs fir'd,</l>
               <l>Our Gallants, they ev'n the Diſeaſe admir'd,</l>
               <l>And hug'd her in their Arms, as ſhe had been</l>
               <l>The only Cauſe to make them Gentlemen.</l>
               <l>All <hi>Portugal, Spain, Italy,</hi> and <hi>Rhine</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Can't pleaſe ſome Palates, o't muſt be <hi>French</hi> Wine;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:153229:9"/>
               <l>Or if it be not ſo, give it the Name,</l>
               <l>It paſſes currant as it were the ſame.</l>
               <l>No Fans, nor Toys, but Theirs, Miſs will receive;</l>
               <l>And for a <hi>French</hi> Dog, what won't Madam give?</l>
               <l>Stor'd with a Breed of Puppies of this Strain,</l>
               <l>Will a Half-broken Merchant raiſe again.</l>
               <l>Then for their Paintings, nothing can come nigh</l>
               <l>Their curious Touches that can pleaſe the Eye;</l>
               <l>A Lady's Chamber will catch cold without 'em:</l>
               <l>As for <hi>French</hi> Watches, they are ſtill about 'em.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>French</hi> Plays and Novels too, are lik'd the beſt,</l>
               <l>And <hi>French</hi> Tranſlating late much in requeſt:</l>
               <l>Put but an Author of that Countrey's Name</l>
               <l>I' th' Title-Page, it gives ev'n Nonſence fame.</l>
               <l>And now ſince theſe, and more, are ſo in vogue,</l>
               <l>We pray, among the reſt, accept their Rogue.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>On the impartial Commendation Of <signed>your Humble Servant <hi>J. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="narrative">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153229:9"/>
            <head>THE French Rogue: Or, The LIFE of Monſieur <hi>RAGO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>An Exact and Pleaſant Relation of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentage; early and monſtrous Birth, being born with Hair and Teeth, five Months after his Mother was marry'd: And of the Suſpicion of his Legitimacy. The Diſcourſe of the Goſſips. A Story of a Barley Child. And what elſe materially happen'd on this Introductory Occaſion.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>AS for my Birth, it may be term'd <hi>Preternatural,</hi> above the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Courſe of Nature, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her, ſomewhat Monſtrous, as in the Sequell I ſhall demonſtrate; and great
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153229:10"/> Diſputes aroſe about my Legitima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>As for my Parentage, the Father that owned me, was one Monſieur <hi>Ragoue de Verſailles,</hi> who had a little Country Seat near to that aſpiring Palace, whoſe Statelineſs has created ſo much Wonder and Commendation. He had ſpent his younger years in Amours and Intrigues with the Fair Sex, though very unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in his Adventures of Knight-Erran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, as having ſquander'd away his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony in relieving diſtreſſed Damſels: ſo that being doubly deſtitute of Money and Friends, he betook him to his laſt ſhift; which was, to leave the ſoft Tents of <hi>Venus,</hi> and enter into thoſe of <hi>Mars.</hi> But the Armies being at that time in Quarters, he had leaſure to repair to his own Manſion; which having been roughly uſed by the ſurly Winds, who had cuffed off a great part of its Cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, was like that wherein Pope <hi>Urbin,</hi> a Fiſherman's Son, was born, and of which, in his Pontifical Pride, he uſed ſcoffingly to make mention of ſaying, He came of an Illuſtrious Houſe; for by reaſon of the ſcarcity of Money
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153229:10"/> to repair it, the Sun darted in his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Rays at a great many more places than the Windows.</p>
               <p>As for his Diet, which otherwiſe muſt have been near as ſlender as that of a Chamelion's, he frequently reſorted to the Houſe of <hi>Villezaroy,</hi> at <hi>Verſailles,</hi> which adjoyn'd to the Royal Palace, who liberally diſpens'd his Bounty to all that appear'd any thing like Gentlemen, by keeping a Table on purpoſe to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain them.</p>
               <p>Here, as the lucky Stars would have it, he became acquainted, and was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperately ſmitten with the irreſiſtable Glances of my fair Mother's ſparkling Eyes. She being an intreaguing Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, ſoon perceiv'd by his ſteady and eager gazing on her, and the Sighs that ſometimes would unpremeditatedly 'ſcape the Priſon of his Boſom: yet as ſhe had ſerved many others, ſhe ſeemed ignorant of his Paſſion, and careleſs of the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Services he render'd her, as he found Occaſion to tender 'em in the moſt obliging manner, when he thought he might beſt nick the Critical Minute of gaining her Affections.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:153229:11"/>
               <p>Now, ſome inquiſitive Coxcomb or other may be deſirous to know her Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract and Quality: Wherefore, not to leave this Particular undiſcuſs'd, I ſhall (as far as I learn'd from her ſelf, which, I believe, was all ſhe knew) clear the Point, and give him Satisfaction</p>
               <p>Though ſhe had been well educated, her Birth was but mean, holding her Rank among the Taylor's Daughters of <hi>Orleance,</hi> the Place where ſhe ſuck'd in her firſt Air; and was at twelve years old left to ſhift for her ſelf, her Parents then ſtepping into the other World, and leaving her as much of this World, as by her Induſtry and Ingenuity ſhe could procure of it, for a Portion, or Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence. She was, indeed, of a very preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant or ſagacious Wit and Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, quick of Apprehenſion, and had a Memory very tenacious; ſo that having trudg'd on foot-back to <hi>Verſailles,</hi> in a pretty janty Garb, ſhe ſoon got into Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, at firſt, to tend a Lady's Child; and then to be Lawndry-Maid to Fair <hi>Lucinda,</hi> a Marquis's Daughter: and ſo perfectly, in little time, learn'd the Art of Wheedling and Flattery; which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153229:11"/> ſhe carry'd on ſo ſmoothly, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny were inſenſibly drawn into a good liking of her facetious way of Diſcourſe and Carriage; and ſo infaſcinated at length they were, that they found them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves uneaſie without her Company <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Converſation, and therefore much co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veted it.</p>
               <p>She was not ſlow in perceiving the Aſcendant ſhe had over them upon this account, and reſolved to turn it to her Advantage. She had frequent B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>bes from their amorous Admirers, to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them, deliver Letters, or plead their Love-ſick Cauſes or Plaints to the Charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fair Ones: which ſhe did in ſo op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune and moving a time and manner, that Succeſs uſually attended her Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours. She often, on the other hand, manag'd the Ladies Intreagues, and was conſcious of their ſtoln Pleaſures. She was (it being a thing very rarely found in the Sex) excellent at ſealing up a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret from the Eyes and Ears of babbling Fame; impriſoning what they intruſted her with, as ſecurely in her Boſom, as a Silk-worm houſed in a ſtrong Box; and made it part of her buſineſs to ſecure
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153229:12"/> their Honours and Reputations, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide them Country Retirements, and faithful Nurſes, when Nature compell'd them to disburthen the Products of their ſtoln Pleaſures; excuſing their Abſence, if Enquiry was made, by informing the Inquiſitive, That my young Lady was gone to paſs ſome Days with her Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Relations, at their Rural Manſions; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ſometimes ſhe was ſick, and could no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> admit of Viſitants; carrying it ſo demurely and ſerious in all her Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, that no ground was left to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mize: She told 'em an <hi>Aeſop</hi>'s Fable for a Veracity. But being young and ſprite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, full of youthful Blood, gay and witty, ſhe thought her Beauty ſuffer'd injury, not to be enjoyed as well as others; and thereupon ſet her Sprindgs, and threw out her Baits and Allurements for Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocks and Gudgeons, where ſhe perceiv'd any Game, or tendency to Sport or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit: and many ſhe took, to her great Advantage; among the reſt, a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis's Son; who (not to be tedious with you) finding, as I ſuppoſe, and as ſhe never without Bluſhes deny'd, that he had given her ſo much Lambſwooll,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153229:12"/> that her Belly began to ſwell; upon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, my Father was fallen in Love with her, for his own Reputation (being then marry'd to a beautiful Lady) made up the Match, and gave them a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Farm to begin the World, as I may ſay, a new with. My Father, who had been a long time under the gripes of Neceſſity, was over-joy'd, that at laſt, as he thought, ſome propitious Star had ſmiled on him, or that he had now found his good Angel, and mightily hugg'd himſelf in the little revival of his Fortune; ſhe having over and above brought him 400 Crowns gotten in Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and the fore-mention'd intreaguing Buſineſſes.</p>
               <p>They liv'd very happily together, always Billing and Cooing like two Turtles, till at the end of five Months, being in bed with her, all on a ſudden ſhe was taken with a violent Pain, the true cauſe of which ſhe could no longer diſſemble, but taking him about the Neck, almoſt ſtiflng him with Kiſſes, and bedewing his Cheeks with Tears, intreated him to riſe and call a Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife. At this he ſtarted, and mutter'd
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153229:13"/> his Reſentments and Diſcontent between his Teeth; but finding that it was but too true, and that there was now no other remedy, out he jumps, and as ſecretly as he could, brought in the good Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men at a Back-door, as knowing what was done was paſt preventing; and to blow his Horns, would but diſturb the Neighbours, at ſuch an unſeaſonable hour. My Mother was active and live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and in a ſhort ſpace, by the help of the Generation-Drawer, I crept thorough the narrow Paſſage of Nativity, into the World, having, contrary to the uſual Birth of other Children, indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent long Hair on my Head; and when one of the Women went to clap me to her Breaſt, not ſuſpecting any danger, the reſt of the Goſſips thought ſhe had been falling in Labour too, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected more Hot-Suppings; for ſhe roared out in a piteous manner, and would have thrown me from her Arms, but that, like a Wolf, I hung too faſt by the Teeth at her Nipple, and made a crimſon trickling deſcend her panting Hill of warm Snow; which preſag'd what bloody work I would make before
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153229:13"/> I have done with the VVorld. VVith much adoe, and the help of the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife's Bodkin, they made me quit my hold; and all of them wonder'd to ſee my Phangs ſo long and ſharp, every one ſpending a Verdict on me, as their Fancies and Opinions led 'em, as to what theſe unuſual Prodromo's might fore-run, or ſignifie, in the whole Series of my Life.</p>
               <p>By this time, the VVeather being Cold, my Father advertiſed of his Spouſe's ſafe Delivery, adventur'd into the Chamber, wrap'd in his Cloak, walking up and down in querpo, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring, by his furious Motion, and ſullen Looks, he was much troubl'd at what had happen'd; which he fear'd would reflect upon him, and redound to his Diſgrace and Affront. My Mother call'd often to him with abundance of honey VVords, as, My Dear, My Bird, My Chuck, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> why are you ſo ſtrange to me at this time; I prithee, Love, draw nearer, and kiſs me. But all would not do, he anſwer'd her never a word, but ſtill kept his Motion, with a wrinkled Fore-head, and bended Brows.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153229:14"/> The good VVomen ſeeing this, and not being ignorant of the Cauſe of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance, when in another caſe it would have been a Comfort and Delight to him, thinking to put him out of his Dumps, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd me, by this time, finely dreſs'd, and ſmiling, ſaid, Pray, Monſieur, turn about, and look upon your hopeful Off-ſpring; your very Picture, I proteſt and vow: Oh, ſweet Babe! Look here! Look here! its Fathers none Noſe, Month, Chin, and every thing ſo like you!—A Pox! (reply'd he, muttering in a ſurly Tone) I know not but it may be like the Father; but then (fetching a deep Sigh, continu'd he) it can't be like me:—VVhy ſo? VVhy ſo? (ſays Mother Mid-night, who bore up briskly to him, and wanting her Fore-Teeth, ſputter'd in his Face, through her earneſtneſs of ſpeaking.)—VVhat! (ſaid he) a Five Month's Child, ſo large and luſty, and mine! Tell me no more on't (biting his Nails) it can never, never. be, (and then ſtampt and fretted?)—Not be! Not be! (reply'd ſhe haſtily, ſtill purſuing him as he walk'd about,) Upon my corporal Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153229:14"/> I proteſt it may be, and has been a hundred times, to my knowledge; therefore, pray Sir, have but patience to hear me, and I'll ſoon convince you. Ay! As how? As how? (ſaid he, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining to leſſen his Anger, and liſten to her.)—VVhy (ſaid ſhe) Don't you ſee, VVheat is ſowed in <hi>September,</hi> and yet it is but ripe in <hi>August?</hi> And, Don't every one that knows any thing of Countrey Affairs, ſee, that Barley ſow'd in the beginning of <hi>March,</hi> is ripe as ſoon, or ſooner; why, here's Five Month's difference in the Grain, and this pretty Babe here, want<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but Four: Dod a bleſh it and ſhaveit, this is a Barley Child, take my VVord for't; and as for the next, you need not doubt but it will be a VVheat Child; and therefore, pray Sir, ſet your Heart at reſt, and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, and thankful for what God has ſent you.</p>
               <p>This a little clear'd up the angry; Cloud that hung on his Brow, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a Storm; and though he was not ſo ignorant, as altogether to credit the old Gypſey, yet finding he muſt acquieſce, and the ſooner the better,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153229:15"/> he gave my Mother a reconciling Buſs, or two, who crouded two Louid'ors into his Hand: with which going to the next Tavern, he waſh'd away Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row from his Heart in good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <p>How he was admired for his large Size and Comelineſs, in his Infancy: How a Great Lady ſeeing him in the Streets, took a Fancy to him, had him under her Tuition, by the Conſent of his Parents; put him to School: And of many things that befell him there, in the Juvenile Progreſs of his Learning, and little Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueries.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>BEing tumbled into the VVorld in the manner before recited, without (as I ever heard on) any Blazing-Stars, or Prodigie fore-running or attending my Birth, I was brought up by Hand: for a Suckler dreaded my ſharp Phangs, as much as a Shipwreck'd Sailor, float<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the VVaves towards ſome friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Shore, do's the meeting of a Shark;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153229:15"/> or the Egyptians, near <hi>Nilus,</hi> an Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gator. As I was of an extraordinary Bigneſs, when I thruſt my Head out of Nature's dark Working-Room, being luſtily cramm'd by my tender and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent Mother, I grew a-pace, and came to my Legs and Speech to Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, before Children that had been born a great many Months before me did, or were expected to do; ſo that many Perſons made it their buſineſs to pretend ſham-Errants to our Houſe, on no other purpoſe than to ſee me: and the Laſſes took a ſingular pleaſure in doudling, kiſſing me, and feeling my Cock; which, in Infancy, promiſed what it has ſince performed to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of the Fair Sex.</p>
               <p>I no ſooner was ſo fledg'd, that I could run about without a Rowler or Leading-ſtrings; but a great Lady paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by our Gate in her Coach, eying me narrowly, was mightily taken with my Phyſiognomy, and pretty manner of Tatling to my diminutive Play-Fellows; who calling me to her, and almoſt ſmothering me with Kiſſes, demanded whoſe pretty Boy I was? Nor could
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153229:16"/> ſhe forbear ſmiling, when inſtead of an Anſwer to her Demand, ſeeing her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate white Breaſts, meander'd with Azure Veins, rendring them very charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and tempting to my Eyes, I fell not only to nuzling, but ſtroaking and play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them: At laſt, ſhe got out of me, who my Father and Mother were; and underſtood, by my pointing to the Houſe, the place of their Abode. It ſeems, this beautiful Creature was, by her own ambitious Inclination to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and the Perſwaſion of her Parents, marry'd to an old fumbling Count; with whom ſhe had liv'd five Years without any Child, or hopes of having one by him; and therefore, to upbraid his Impotency, or ſtir him up, if poſſible, to a more active Vigour, or frequenter Repetition of the Leſſon ſhe lov'd, ſhe was deſirous to have me to ſet as a Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern before his Eyes, and thereupon or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd her gaudy glittering four Wheel'd Movement to drive nearer to our Door.</p>
               <p>My Father and Mother happening to be at home, wonder'd what great Viſitant this might be; but more, when
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153229:16"/> they ſaw her hugging their hopeful Iſſue in her Arms: They accoſted her with what Complements, on a ſudden, bolted into their Heads; and ſhe return'd them ſuitable Civilities: but when ſhe came to ſtart the Queſtion, of parting with me, and what Great Things ſhe would do for me, my Mother, whoſe Darling I was (though by this time ſhe had ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Son) ſeemed very averſe to it: But my Father, who ſeldom looked on me with pleaſing Eyes, it ſtill running in his Mind, that I was none of his Beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, was more attentive to her Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; and prevail'd with my Mother, that within ten days I ſhould be ſent to her Ladyſhip; ſhe, by reaſon of her great Quality, not being unknown to either of them: And ſo having given me a fervent Kiſs, or two, and clapping a ſmall Necklace of Pearl, as an Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of her Kindneſs, about my Neck, ſhe took her leave, highly ſatisfy'd in this Adventure.</p>
               <p>She was no ſooner gone, but my Mother, dropping ſome Tears, repented her Conſent; and laboured, by many Arguments and Perſwaſions, to have
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153229:17"/> revok'd and null'd it: But my Father, more willing to be rid of me, perſwaded her to acquieſce in a Separation that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed ſo much, not only to mine, but, as he ſtrongly urged, the Advancement of our Family; and accordingly I was ſent, under the ſafe Conduct of <hi>Margery</hi> our Maid; and fancy'd I became, as it were, the adopted Son of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Daughter.</p>
               <p>The old Lord, I perceiv'd at my firſt arrival, was a little doubtful whether his young Lady had told him the truth; or that being ſenſible of his Inabilities, it might be her own Off-ſpring by ſome duſty Lover, upon his abſence on an Embaſſie, at the time he fancy'd I might be made and brought into the World. But upon a ſober Enquiry, and the coming of my Mother to viſit me, this blew over, and he found himſelf oblig'd, in Honour, to crave Madam's Pardon for his unjuſt Suſpicion; and I was ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly cloathed, entertained, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended; and by my pretty Diſcourſe, and little Apiſh Tricks, diverted my Lady in her Fits of Melancholy, more than her Buffoon, or Monkey: and for
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153229:17"/> my better Accompliſhment, being ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd at my Tenth Year, without many other remarkable Tranſactions of my Life, that no Qualifications might be wanting in me worthy of acquiring, and for the Improvement of Education, I was put under the Tuition of a famous Peda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, or School-Maſter, who ſpared no Correction for the benefit or furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Inſtruction.</p>
               <p>I learn'd to read and write French pretty tollerable the firſt Year; and by converſing with an Italian Youth, I pretty well underſtood that Language: but the next Year, being put to the dull Grammatical Methods and Rules of Scholaſtical Education, it grew tireſom to me, my magnanimous Spirit being by Nature exalted above it; yet having with great difficulty, in another Peram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation of the Sun through the Twelve Signs of the Zodiack, crouded my ſelf into the company of Adverbs, Prepoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Interjections, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with which I did ſo kick, cuff &amp; ſcuffle, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding my Maſter gave all poſſible Aſſiſtance to his Diſciple, yet he found the Opponents too crabbed to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153229:18"/> which unhappy Conteſts fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ended in moſt cruel Flagella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that made me but the more ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born and regardleſs, though he plough'd and furrow'd my tender Buttocks, till they carry'd the Marks and Characters of all Languages on them. Shame, and deſire of Revenge, ſtopt my Complaints, or my good-natur'd Lady would not have ſuffer'd me to have undergone ſuch Severities: which Revenge, as ſweet to me as Eggs and Muſcadine, I accompliſh'd before I intended to take my Farewell, as will appear in the next Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:153229:18"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of his Maſter's Severity towards him, by reaſon of his neglecting his Learning, and following his Sports, to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witting and defrauding his Companions: And how, by divers comical Tricks and Intrigues, he purſu'd his Revenge, cauſed his Miſtreſs to run away with one of the Scholars, and all the Money and Plate; which breaks his Maſter's Heart, and ſo he return'd to his Lady.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>TO divert the Trouble my Maſter's Severity put me into, I bent my ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy upon all manner of boyiſh Recreations, and became very expert therein, beyond the reſt of my Companions, as Tipcat, Cricket, Span-Farthing, Skittle-Pins, Cudgels, Wreſtling, and the like; by which, over and above the Allowance I had from my Lady, whom rarely I went to viſit, but ſhe crouded a Crown into my Hand at parting, I gained con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderably in Money and Experience; and finding my old Pedegogue covetous,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153229:19"/> I fell into a dextrous way to buy off my Faults with Preſents of curious Fruits, and choice Wines, which I pretended my Mother, or my Lady, had ſent me, and ſometimes, he being none of the richeſt or beſt Husbands, with Money I ſuggeſted to have found in the ſtreets; which ſo charm'd him, that much of my uſual Puniſhment was abated, though my Learning made no better progreſs; yet I heinouſly reſenting how ſcurvily he had uſed me, the deſire of Revenge ſtill run in my Mind and I was reſolved, in ſome meaſure or other, to cry quits with him at parting.</p>
               <p>I caſt in my mind various ways how to bring it about: ſometimes one Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject liked me, and then another joſtled it out of the way; ſome ſeemed eaſie to be accompliſhed, others preſented them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in frightful Idea's, full of Hazard and Danger, and very difficult to be brought about, and me to come off with ſafety; inſomuch, that although I was very quick at Invention, eſpecially of Miſchief, which my School-fellows had frequently experienc'd, to their ſmart and loſs: yet here, I confeſs, I
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153229:19"/> was at a plunge; but not long after, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ucky, or unlucky Hit (call it which you pleaſe) came into my Noddle, though ſomewhat, as yet, undigeſted, and not well ſhapen: I had obſerved the oldeſt of our Scholars, who had arriv'd at nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years of age, and was ſubſtituted by my Maſter, ſometimes, as a kind of an Uſher to ſupply his Place, when he had a mind to be among his toping Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and by his Complaints, had many times cauſed me a ſmarting, to have a leer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Inclination towards my Miſtreſs, who being ſpritely and gay, in her youthful Blood, and before, his Chamber-Maid, had marry'd the Dotard for a more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and regular Subſiſtance, and larger Command, and that ſhe had not declin'd the Civilities the young Amoriſt omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted no Occaſion to tender her. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, upon theſe Obſervations there muſt be ſomething more than ordinary in the winding up of the bottom, and therefore became a more intent and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igent Spy upon their Actions, critically marking their Glances, Smiles and Winks, and ſcrutenizing the niceſt Symbols of Love, till I verily believed my Maſter
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153229:20"/> was very near, if not already enter'd the Kingdom of Cuckoldom; then I began to contrive Ginns and Snares to catch him in the uneaſie and dangerous Trap of Jealouſie; and by degrees, led him into greater Miſhaps and Perturbations, if poſſible.</p>
               <p>One Evening, my Miſtreſs feigned her ſelf indiſpos'd, and would needs go to bed ſooner than ordinary; which made me more ſedulous in putting my ſelf on the watch for a further Diſcovery: and thereupon, ſneaking up before her, as ſoft as if I had trod upon Eggs, I was ſoon conceal'd behind the Arras. She was ſcarcely enter'd, and in a Poſture charming enough to receive her Lover, but I heard one trip up Stairs, and give a gentle rap or two at the Door. Upon this, ſhe jumpt out of Bed, and gave ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance to the Party I had all along ſuſpected to be more welcome to her Arms than my Maſter. Having almoſt ſtifled him with Kiſſes, and whiſper'd many endearing Expreſſions into his Ear; for it ſeems, being one of <hi>Cupid</hi>'s Novices, he was ſomewhat baſhful in encountering theſe Enjoyments, he
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153229:20"/> quickly unſtript, and his lovely <hi>Venus</hi> as ſoon infolded him in her Arms; and ſo they began a Citizen's galloping pace at his firſt ſetting out; but after fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Repetitions, tired and ſatiated with ſweet Enjoyments, after ſome pretty Murmurings, and Love-toying, ſo long a ſilence enſu'd, that I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded them a-ſleep; and ſo intending to ſteal away undiſcover'd, and ſend up my Maſter, I crept from 'em as ſilent as a Ghoſt: but as I was going out, 'ſpying a Glew-Pot over a glimmering Fire in the Chimney, left there by the forgetfulneſs of the Joiner, who had been cementing the disjointed Frame of a great Looking glaſs that ſtood in the Room, another Whim came into my Head; for perceiving their Opticks faſt cloſed, I with a gentle Hand ſtroak'd them over with the glutinous Materials; and leaving them in that Condition, I lock'd the Door on the out-ſide, and crept down Stairs as ſoftly as I aſcended. I thought indeed to have found old Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head in his Study, where ſometimes he was wont to ſit up late; but peeping through the Key-hole, and perceiving
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153229:21"/> no Light, nor hearing that ſnoaring he uſually made if he fell a-ſleep, and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd his Candle to burn out, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded he was not there; but coming into the Kitchen, I heard the Cook-Maid ſay, I muſt go lay the Key for my Maſter; for he's a ſucking at the Tavern among the old Gang, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he will not come home till his uſual hour of Twelve. This gave larger ſcope to my Invention; and pretending to go to Bed, as the reſt did, I, however, crept down to prepare for his Recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when he ſhould enter. In the firſt place, I drew up a Trap-Door in an Entry he was to paſs, made for the conveniency of emptying or cleanſing the Sink and Bog-houſe, which run under it, and then planted my ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the Outward-Door, with a fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſort of Vizard tied over my Face, with a Cap on, to which a pair of Horns were fixed, that we had ſometimes uſed in our private Maſquerading; and leſt my Cloaths ſhould be know, I had ſtript over my Shoulders an old caſt Black Crape Petticoat; and having a ſmall Rocket in my Breeches, the remainder
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153229:21"/> of the laſt publick Fire-work Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, with my Pocket-Tinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>box I ſtruck, fire, and tinded my Match.</p>
               <p>Being thus accouter'd, he came ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſooner than I expected; and by his grunting, and fumbling for the Key under the Door, I perceiv'd he was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſucky, or addle-Pated: at length he open'd it, yet advanc'd but a few ſteps e're he blunder'd over me, who had laid my ſelf as a Stumbling-block in his way, and miſerably broke his Face a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Pavement; but before he had time to make any noiſe, I had got up and fired my Rocket; by the light of which unexpected fuze, lifting up his batter'd Forehead, and ſeeing my dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Form, concluded me to be no other than the firſt-begotten of <hi>Belzebub,</hi> come to puniſh him for his ſins of the Bottle; upon which, bolting up at a leap, Fear adding Wings to his Feet, he fled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, crying out, <hi>The Devil! The Devil! Help! Help! He has me! He has me!</hi> whilſt I purſu'd with a Fire-drake at his Tail, crying with a hollow and hoarſe Voice, through a Kecks, <hi>Thou art mine,</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:153229:22"/> 
                  <hi>Thou art mine; and with me you ſhall go to the Shades Below.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I had ſcarce ended theſe Words, but the Trap took him, and down he plung'd into the Filth, over Head and Ears; when throwing the unſpent part of my Rocket, which till then I held in my Hand, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, I ſhut down the Door upon him, and was got to my Chamber juſt as it gave the Bounce; which being juſt above the Place, I could hear him bellow out hideouſly, <hi>I'm in Hell! I'm in Hell! Oh, Mercy! Mercy! Mercy!</hi> Which doleful Noiſe alarm'd the neareſt of the Servants, and they rouz'd others; and, to be brief, being directed where he was by the the Noiſe he continually made, they lifted up the Pit-fall, and drew him out, like another <hi>Joſeph,</hi> in a miſerable ſtinking Condition, almoſt ſenſeleſs, through Fear and Stench, won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring how, poſſibly, he could come there, the Door being ſhut ſo cloſe down: but as ſoon as they had given him ſome Spirits to revive him, he frightfully look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about with abrupt Stammerings and Heſitation, aſſur'd them, That a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous ſtump-footed Devil, in a horrid
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153229:22"/> ſhape, vomiting flames of Fire, had ſeiz'd him, juſt as he enter'd the Door, and was carrying him that way, as he believ'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o his Infernal Region; but, upon ſaying an <hi>Ave-Maria,</hi> the Daemon quitted his hold, and vaniſh'd in a Clap of Thunder, that had ſindg'd his Whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers.</p>
               <p>His Fear being a little diſſipated, the pickle he was in, made not only him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but all that were about him, uneaſie, till they had put him into a Bucking-Tub under the Pump, and ſcrubb'd him into ſomewhat a more ſweet and cleanly Condition. Whilſt this was doing, and I not perceiving my Miſtreſs and her Lover all this while to ſtir, reſolved, now I had begun, to go thorough-ſtitch with my Roguery; and therefore, taking an End of Candle that ſtood by me, I light it by the help of my Tinder-box, put it in a Dark-Lanthorn, and creep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing undiſcover'd near their Apartment, ſet an old tatter'd Map of the World, paſted on Canvaſs, and hanging in the Stair-caſe, on fire: and being ſure, that before it could do any harm, it would be diſcover'd by the blazing Light, and ſo
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153229:23"/> concluding I had made Fire-works enough, I crept to Bed again; which I had no ſooner done, but my Ears were ſaluted with the noiſe of <hi>Fire! Fire!</hi> and and could hear my Old Maſter roar out in his Bucking-Tub, <hi>He's come again! He's come again! and will have me! I ſee his Sawcer-Eyes glaring thorough the Caſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment!</hi> and as a Charm againſt the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Fury, mumbl'd over divers Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in the <hi>Roſary,</hi> and rattl'd his Beads.</p>
               <p>The Noiſe of Fire alarm'd the Watch, and they came thund'ring at the Outer-Door; and had the ſooner admittance, becauſe thoſe of the Servants who, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, did not ſuppoſe it to be the Devil, nor his Dam, fancy'd there might be Thieves in the Houſe. The Night-Governour no ſooner advanc'd with his Guard of Bilbo-Blades, but my Maſter took a little Courage, as ſuppoſing now, having Authority on his ſide, they were ſtrong enough to ſcuffle with <hi>Lucifer</hi> himſelf, ſhould he make any further At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt or Diſturbance: but perceiving his dear Wife had not appear'd during all this Noiſe, Hurry and Confuſion, he fell into dreadful Apprehenſions, that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153229:23"/> Demigorgon, in his retreat, might have catcht her napping, and taken her for him, or that, at leaſt, ſome other miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief might have befaln her, and ſo flouncing out of his Tub (like <hi>Lazarillo de Tormes,</hi> in his eſcape, when he was taken and ſhow'd for a monſtrous Sea-Fiſh) he pray'd the Man of Authority, and his Janizary-Tribe, to go with him to the Chamber of his Sweeting; yet Fear ſo ſhook him, that he ſtrain'd Courteſie to make them the Front, that he might have the honour to be in the Front, if they ſhould have occaſion to face-about.</p>
               <p>Their Leaden-heel'd trampling up Stairs, and a bounce or two at the Door, made the two Lovers ſtart out of their ſweet and pleaſant Dreams; and juſt as the Door was opened, (for the Key was ſtill on the out-ſide) they leaped out of Bed in their Shifts; and not being able to ſee, their Eyes being ſo faſt glew'd, but hearing a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Voices, verily ſuppos'd them Thieves and Murtherers, who had kill'd the reſt of the Family, and were come to diſpatch them laſt; wherefore, running
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:153229:24"/> skreaming about the Room, as ſuppoſing themſelves in the dark, tho' ſeveral Lights were brought in, in ſeeking for ſhelter, they tumbl'd headlong over the Stools and Chairs, which I had ſet out of rank for ſome ſuch purpoſe; ſo that my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs's delicate white Buttock turn'd up, and ſhe produc'd her Ace of Trumps for Higheſt, by rolling over; whilſt her young Amoriſt, being hindermoſt, and taking his turn at tumbling, pitch'd directly over a Chair, with his Head be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween her Haunches.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that ſaw them at theſe Vagaries, and they not hearkning to what they ſaid, took them to be a couple of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted Perſons; till my Maſter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in, and putting on his Spectacles, perceiv'd how the Game had gone, and like a good-natur'd Husband, though it fretted his Gall, to be privately injur'd, and publickly diſgrac'd, haſted to cover his dear Wife's naked Beauty, which lay too temptingly expos'd to vulgar Eyes, by carrying her into Bed, and throwing the Cloaths over her. Hearing her Husband's Voice, ſhe was a little com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, as knowing now this was not
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:153229:24"/> the laſt hour ſhe had to live, nor the laſt time ſhe ſhou'd ſerve him ſo, but with hopes of better luck than to be ſo baſely betray'd into a Diſgrace, by over-drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs; yet ſhe alledg'd, ſhe knew not how his Scholar (who was all this while upon his Knees begging Mercy and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs) came into her Chamber, or how their Eyes came to be ſhut up, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it was by Witchcraft: Which the old indulgent Coxcomb comparing with what had befaln himſelf, either that he believ'd it, or that he feign'd he did ſo, to hide the Shame, and hinder theſe Paſſages, as much as he could, from being made publick, concluded, at that time it was ſo; and diſmiſſing the Watch with Money and Thanks, intreating them not to ſcatter any Words abroad of what they had heard and ſeen. But they were no Privy-Counſellors; for in a ſhort time, all the neighbouring Places rung of theſe Adventures</p>
               <p>Warm Milk was immediately brought to unſeal the Eyes of theſe blinded Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; which, with much rubbing, ſtruggling and pain, open'd their Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks (like our Firſt Parents, in Paradiſe,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153229:25"/> when fallen, to bluſh the more at what they had offended in.) My Maſter ſurpreſſing his Anger, ſaid no more of it that Night, but order'd the young Gameſter to his Bed, and went himſelf to another, as not being yet ſweeten'd and air'd ſufficiently to come between my Miſtreſs's Arms, though ſhe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plementally deſir'd it; but with what Sincerity you may imagine.</p>
               <p>Early in the Morning he came to his Spouſe, having broke his Reſt by a thouſand Fancies and Imaginations run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all night in his Head, and labour'd to get out of her the Truth of the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in Generals or Particulars: But ſhe being a cunning Baggage, and having a great aſcendant over his Credulity, perſiſted, it was done by Witchcraft; and ſhe knew no more how it otherwiſe came about, than the Man in the Moon. Reſolving not to give it over ſo, he goes to the Youngſter, and beginning to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine him, bid him freely confeſs, as he hoped for Pardon; for his Miſtreſs had declar'd, That when he crept to Bed to her, ſhe was deceiv'd, and knew not but it was him, her Husband. The
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:153229:25"/> Noddy thinking this to be true, and fearing a Rape, at leaſt, would be laid to his Charge, fell on his Knees, and declar'd, his Miſtreſs tempted him to theſe Enjoyments, by urging the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency of her Husband, and that this was not the firſt by an hundred times. At this my Old Maſter being inrag'd, as ſuppoſing him to be the Contriver of the Miſchiefs that had befaln himſelf, drags him into the School, calls in his Man; and having ty'd our young Cuckold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker, Hand and Foot, croſs a Table, immediately lock'd up his Wife, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a Reſcue; and he fell to cooling his Courage, at ſuch a thraſhing rate, on his Buttocks, that after the tiring him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and the expence of two Brooms, he left ſuch bloody Remembrances, as neither <hi>Bridewell,</hi> or the Cart's-tail, ever produc'd.</p>
               <p>My Miſtreſs hearing the miſerable Outcry her diſtreſſed Gallant made, at laſt ventur'd out at the Window, by the Sheets tied together, and came and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound him, being ready to ſwoon away at ſo piteous a Sight: And (to be brief) ſoon after they ſo plotted, that he going
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:153229:26"/> away in diſcontent, ſhe robb'd my Maſter of all his Money, Plate, and richeſt Things, and follow'd her abler Gameſter to Places of freer Enjoyment: Inſomuch, that Grief ſoon after caſt my Pedagogue into a Fever, and that caſt him into the Grave, and gave me the Revenge and Liberty, with as fine a Come-off as ever I could have wiſhed, and much better than I could reaſonably have expected, though I could have been contented my Old Maſter had had more Wit than to have dwindl'd into the other World upon ſo ſlight Occaſion: yet I have ever made it my Obſervations, That ſuch as ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannize over proſtrate Creatures have neither Hearts nor Courage to face or ſuſtain Croſſes or Afflictions, when they preſs hard upon themſelves.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>He that will triumph o'er a Wretch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrest,</l>
                  <l>Sinks lowest, when by Miſery opprest:</l>
                  <l>The Noble and the Brave, who ſcorn to tread</l>
                  <l>On Worms, when Fortune ſrowns, hold up their Head,</l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:153229:26"/>
                  <l>And dare the threatning Storm, as free from Wrongs,</l>
                  <l>That croud on guilty Minds in fearful throngs.</l>
                  <l>But here, I must confeſs, was no ſuch guilt;</l>
                  <l>My Buttocks ſmarted, without much Blood ſpilt;</l>
                  <l>Yet I too raſh Revenge ſheath'd to the Hilt:</l>
                  <l>Ruin'd a Family at one bold ſtroke,</l>
                  <l>For one's dam'd Whim, who durst my Rage provoke?</l>
                  <l>So have I heard, A Comet, from his Hair</l>
                  <l>Shakes Death and Ruine. Then let all beware,</l>
                  <l>Lest in my Shape a Baſilisk appear,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe darting Eyes ſends out a poyſonous flame,</l>
                  <l>That kills, though unperceiv'd from whence it came;</l>
                  <l>A Shaft of Fate through trembling Air there flies,</l>
                  <l>That Life, through ne'er ſo guarded, can ſurprize.</l>
                  <l>Thus ſpringing Secret Mines, I overthrew</l>
                  <l>That Strength that open Force could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver do.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:153229:27"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How he returns to his Lady. His kind Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception. And contemplating on her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Beauty. How he goes Abroad a Viſiting with her, being conſtituted her Page; and in her Viſit to a great Lady, puts a very comical Trick upon a drouſie Fryer, the Lady's Confeſſor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the Mirth and Wonder of the Family.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>VVE poor Scholars, upon my Maſter's <hi>Exit</hi> into I know not what World, though not at the uſual Tides or Feſtivals Breaking-up, had a long Jubilee, and return'd to our ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Habitations. As for my part, my charitable Lady received me with as much Kindneſs as ſhe did when my lucky Stars threw me firſt in her way: which, in Gratitude, conſtrain'd me to a double-Diligence in obliging her, as far as my tender Years capacitated me. She deck'd me now with finer Plumes than ever, conſtituting me her Page to wait on her at Home and Abroad. And
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:153229:27"/> my Lord was no leſs pleas'd with my little Waggeries, ſpending ſome Hours, in Winter-Nights, to hear me run on in Diſcourſe of Childiſh Recreations; and if I bolted out any thing that made my Lady fall into a Fit of Laughter, he ſeemed over-joy'd; for he Lov'd her entirely, even to Doating; and when, at any time, ſhe was diſcompoſed, he ſuited his Humour to ſympathize with her in Melancholy: for, indeed, ſhe was a very Curious Creature, Caſt in one of Nature's choiceſt Moulds; ſo that when ſhe was Form'd, no doubt, our General Dame cry'd, <hi>A Lucky Hit;</hi> and reſerv'd her as a Pattern of Beauty.</p>
               <p>Young as I was, I could ſeldom, when in her Preſence, keep my Eyes fixed upon any other Object. I had heard much Talk of <hi>Venus;</hi> and I concluded, if there was a Rarity in Creation, of that Sex, this muſt be ſhe. Thus, in my Childiſh Imaginations, I form'd Idea's to my ſelf; and that ſo ſtrongly, that finding her, one day, ſleeping upon a Couch, I took the boldneſs to rumple her ruby Lips with Kiſſes. At which ſhe wak'd, and ſmiled; yet blamed my
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:153229:28"/> Preſumption, and told me, I muſt not preſume to offer any more ſuch unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Rudeneſs, leſt I forfeited the Eſteem and Favours ſhe had beſtowed upon me.</p>
               <p>Abaſh'd with this Reprimand, which, however had ſomething of Mildneſs and Serenity in it, I retir'd at an aweful diſtance, and bending one Knee to the Ground, humbly implor'd her Pardon for my unadviſed Raſhneſs. Well, ſaid ſhe, I give it you, and take it as only proceeding from the Effects of youthful Folly, but beware how you tranſgreſs any more in this nature. I promis'd her I would not, but ever ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve my Diſtance and Reſpect to her Ladyſhip She could not forbear ſmiling at the Simplicity of my Excuſe; and ſo with ſome Cringes and Scrapes I quitted her Retiring-Room, and left her to her Repoſe.</p>
               <p>The next Morning, ſhe gave Order I ſhould wait on her Abroad. At which I was not a little over-joy'd, as conceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, like thoſe in the Frozen North, upon the Suns retiring, all was gloomy and dark when ſhe withdrew herſelf
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:153229:28"/> from my ſight; yet was ſo ignorant, that I proteſt I knew not then to what my Deſires tended, being, as I may ſay, in <hi>Embrio,</hi> a formleſs and diſorder'd Chaos, or Confuſion, till maturer Years had poliſh'd my green Underſtanding.</p>
               <p>The Coach being ready about Ten in the Morning Abroad we went, and my Lady payed Viſits to divers Perſons of Honour, without any long ſtay; till at laſt, coming to a great Counteſs's Houſe, very pleaſant and delightful in its curious Situation and Gardens, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling the Primitive Paradiſe; ſhe reſolv'd not only to dine there, but ſpend a part of the Heat of the Day under the Umbrage of thoſe cool and ſpreading Shades: of which I was not a little glad, for my Belly grumbl'd for an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote againſt Emptineſs. Our Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment was very ſumptuous, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Diſcourſes paſs'd of State Affairs, and ſometimes of Amorous Intreagues. I, though I Waited, and a Stranger, not being minded, by way of Scruple, by reaſon of my Nonnage; yet as little as I ſeemed to regard it, I could perceive my Lady ſmile, with her dazling Eyes,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:153229:29"/> on a florid brisk young Caveliero, and many interchangeable Glances paſs'd between them; and having heard him nam'd, I concluded, by what had been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported of my Mother upon my ſo ſudden coming into the World, for whoſe ſake it was that ſhe kindly entertain'd me; for this Gallant, upon a more ſtrict En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, in which I was not wanting among the Servants, proved to be the very Man that Fame had whiſper'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad for my True Father: The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of which did not a little ſwell my Pride; for I was naturally Ambitious, and, methoughts, had a Mind that ſoar'd at things above my reach. Once or twice I thought to take an opportunity to lay Claim to him before we parted from that Houſe; but then Fear and Shame check'd my Reſolves, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing within me commanded me to wave it, leſt being miſtaken, I repented my ſawcy Preſumption: ſo that leaving, him and my Lady, as I was comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, for the more privacy of Diſcourſe in the Walks, after Dinner, I went to take a View of the Apartments, ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling up and down by my ſelf, admiring
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:153229:29"/> now the curious Pictures on the Stair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſes, and in the Galleries; then the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Fret-work, and gilded Cielings; by and by, the curious Painted Glaſs in the Windows; till paſſing many ſtately Rooms, I at laſt came into the Dormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, or Sleeping-Apartment for the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; and what ſhould my Eyes fix on, as the firſt Object, but a huge Two-handed Fat Fryer, of the Order (as I perceived by his Habit) of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> lying on a Couch on the Ground, faſt aſleep, and ſnoaring like a Rattle-Snake; and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever pleaſant Dream, of the Confeſſion of ſome pretty wanton Wench, had come into his Head, I know not, but his Label of Mortality, he decumbing on his Back, had broke Priſon; and, May-Pole like, diſdain'd its Statelineſs ſhould be hid. I was upon this, once or twice, about to call the Maids to take Meaſure of it; but being in a ſtrange Place, I knew not whether it might be taken for a Jeſt, or an Affront; and therefore thought it better to leave him in ſuch a Rampant Poſture, than to expoſe his Vigour to the Longing Appetites of buxom Laſſes: But to further my miſchievous Deſign,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:153229:30"/> and compell Father Shaveling to ſing <hi>Ave-Maria</hi> backward, to the Tune of, <hi>The Millers Gelding the Devil,</hi> in a little Houſe hard by, I heard a Calf blating, as bemoaning the Abſence of his Dam: whereupon lifting up the Latch, I looſed him from his Stall and brought him to the Prieſt, to make his Confeſſion of being an Hungry; and guided him ſo near, that he ſoon eſpied what I directed him to: which he taking for his Mammy's Teat, greedily ſeiz'd it, and fell to tugging, frisking his Tail, and ſoft blating, till he had lugg'd Sir <hi>Domine</hi> off the Couch. In the mean while, having ſoftly tied his Legs and Hands, to prevent his diſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging himſelf, I writ upon a Board over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againſt him, with a Phoſphoros, <hi>Woe be to you Whoremongers!</hi> which immediately, as it's nature is, fell into a Blue Flame, burning in large Characters, plain and legible, which the Darkneſs of the Place render'd more dreadful. Upon which, I vaniſh'd, to liſten, at a diſtance, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcover'd, what might be the Event.</p>
               <p>This Babe of a Cow, as I ſuppoſe, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no Milk come, ſuck'd and nibbl'd ſo hard, that he wak'd the drouſie Prieſt;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:153229:30"/> who ſeeing himſelf thus ſurpriz'd, and the dreadful Hand-Writing on the Wall, betwixt Pain and Fear, made him roar out, like <hi>Perillus</hi> in <hi>Phalarus</hi>'s Brazen Bull. Which alarming the Maids in the Pantry, they came running to ſee what the Matter was: But ſeeing their ghoſtly Father ſo entangl'd, and ſeiz'd on by a Cloven-ſooted Creature, and the harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Flame ſtill burning (its nature being ſo to continue about a Quarter of an Hour) they run out skreaming; whilſt he, in a lamentable Tone, cry'd after them, to bring his Pot of Holy-Water, to douſe the ſuppoſed Daemon, and ſend him packing to the <hi>Red Sea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Noiſe theſe Wenches made, brought ſeveral young Ladies, and the reſt of the Servants: who underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Cauſe of the Out cry and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance, peep'd in at the Door, but durſt adventure no further; till with much ſtruggling, the good Father got looſe, and came running out among them, Croſſing himſelf, the Calf ſtill following at his Breech, puſhing him forward, and nuzling in ſearch of the miſtaken Teat; which now depriv'd of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:153229:31"/> its Vigour, hung dangling out; which caus'd the Females to ſcamper and ſqueek: but one of the Men-Servants, more bold than the reſt, perceiving the Prieſt's Errour, laid hold on the Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>footed Animal: which undeceiving the Aſſembly, turn'd their Panick Fear into loud Laughter.</p>
               <p>The Prieſt, upon this, bit his Thumbs, raged, ſtampt and fretted, drawing his Knife, to take bloody Revenge upon his Affronter; but was hinder'd, and the Matter excus'd, as happening by Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, through the Innocency and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake of the Beaſt; but how the ſtrange flaming Hand-Writing came, they were at a loſs to define, ſome of them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding this happen'd as a Judgment to diſcover the Secret Sins of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor. However, it made a great Noiſe in the Family, ſo that the Prieſt, through Shame and Anger, ſhut him up in his Chamber, and appear'd no more that day in publick, though he was often ſent for to Prayers.</p>
               <p>My Lady, upon our going Home, perceiving me laughing heartily at what had paſs'd, and knowing how I was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:153229:31"/> to Archneſs and Waggery, charg'd me to tell her if I had any hand in the Matter. When not being able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal any thing from her, I told her plainly how I had manag'd the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treague, with all the Circumſtances that attended the Adventure. At which ſhe could not forbear ſmiling and bluſhing: and when we come to our Manſion, it ſerved for Table-Talk at Supper; and ſo tickled my Old Lord's Fancy, that with ſtraining too much in an exceſſive Fit of Laughter, he bepiſt himſelf, and was forc'd to haſten into the Laundry for a dry Clout; which proved a new Subject for Merriment.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus my ſmall Rogueries crept up by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees,</l>
                  <l>Till grown to Monſters frightfuller than theſe;</l>
                  <l>No Conjuring Monk ſuch Magick Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief wrought,</l>
                  <l>As I, by Roguiſh Wit, on the World's Stage have brought.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:153229:32"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How undertaking to Travel with a young Lord, he viewed ſeveral ſtately Towns and Cities; gives a Deſcription of the <hi>Alpes,</hi> in his Paſſage; and the Strange, tho' very Comical and Pleaſant Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they met with in their first Night's Lodging in <hi>Italy:</hi> And other Matters.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>NExt Opportunity I had to wait on my Lady in private, ſhe demanded whether I was willing to go with the young Gentleman that walk'd with her in the Garden, to travel? urging how much it would be to my Advantage, for the ſeaſoning and accompliſhing my Youth with all thoſe Qualifications that might hereafter render me accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to my Superiors. At this, I fix'd my Eyes on the Ground, and appear'd melancholy; not but that I had a great Deſire to Ramble, but thought it intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable to be divorc'd, by a tedious Exile, to foregoe the Pleaſure I took in gazing on her Charming and Angelical Features.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:153229:32"/> But ſhe urg'd it ſo far, that at laſt I conſented, if my Mother's Approbation might be had. Which ſhe undertook to procure; and with ſome difficulty ſhe yielded; and the rather, becauſe her Husband, my reputed Father, had ſworn to be the death of me, if ever I came in his way, for ſaying, among my <hi>quondam</hi> School-fellows, when they upbraidingly ſtarted a Suſpicion of my Legitimacy, That I had rather be accounted the Baſe Son of that Noble Lord they twitted me with, than the True Off-ſpring of that pitiful Pimping Cuckold, Monſieur <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goue:</hi> Which unadviſed Words, fooliſhly let drop, were ſo loudly babbl'd abroad, that by one means or other it came to his Ear. My Mother and I thereupon, parted with Tears; and the next Day, the young Lord <hi>de Villeroy,</hi> Son to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis of that Name (for ſuch I found him to be) came to our Houſe with a very ſplendid Equipage, to take his leave of my Old Lord, but eſpecially of my Young Lady, who was his Kinſwoman at ſome diſtance: and underſtanding, as he deſired, I was to accompany him, he ſeem'd mightily pleas'd; and more,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:153229:33"/> when asking me divers Queſtions, he found me endow'd with ſingular Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Parts, and a prompt Wit. My loving Lady cauſed her Steward to furniſh me with all things neceſſary, and a Cock-horſe I mounted. Far we had not rid, but feeling in the Pockets of my Horſe-man's Coat, I found a Box, and in it Forty Luid'ors, or Seventeen and ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penny Pieces of Gold. I preſently knew the fair Hand from whence they came, and bleſs'd my lucky Stars, and her more bright in my Eyes than any Conſtella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whoſe Bounty had rain'd this ſhower of Gold upon me.</p>
               <p>We travell'd through divers fair and pleaſant Countreys, took a View of many ſtately Cities and Burroughs: and I obſerv'd, in all the Places where we Lodg'd and Inn'd, my Lord had a more peculiar Regard of me, than of any other of his Retinue; which, he told me, was for my Lady's ſake, who had tenderly recommended me to his Care. Paſſing the huge rugged <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine</hi> Mountain, by that narrow Paſſage that leads out of <hi>France,</hi> I perceived, though the Weather was extreme Hot
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:153229:33"/> at the Bottom, we were on the Top, as in a Winter-ſeaſon, the Air being Thin and Sharp; the Snow, though in the Middle of Summer, lay thick, and undiſſolv'd in divers Valleys, or Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows of the Rock; and in heavy lowr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Weather, a Sea of Watry Clouds floated beneath us; the Sun ſhining, and all being ſerene and calm over our Heads. In four Days we paſſed thoſe mighty Mountains, and enter'd <hi>Italy;</hi> it being his purpoſe to viſit that once Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Country in times paſt, renown'd for its pleaſant Situation and Fertility throughout the VVorld, but now, through the Pride and Contention of the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lazineſs of the Commonalty, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ope's of <hi>Rome</hi>'s Uſurpation and Tyranny over a great part of the moſt flouriſhing Provinces, it is much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay'd, and its Grandeur dwindl'd into ſcarcely any thing that may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd to its former State and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity, many Caſtles and Villages lying waſte and ruinated, without Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants or Owners; ſo that the Roads, by reaſon of the <hi>Banditti,</hi> and other ſorts of Outlaws, Robbers, and Rapparees,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:153229:34"/> are very dangerous to travel without a ſtrong Guard, eſpecially by Strangers who are unacquainted with ſuch Turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings as may enable them to avoid their uſual Lurking-places; as I found by woful Experience, which ſufficiently puniſh'd me for my former VVagge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, but harden'd and prompted me in greater Miſchiefs.</p>
               <p>VVe paſſed to the Confines of <hi>Naples<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> without meeting with any conſiderabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Adventures worth relating, unleſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome uneaſie Quarters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for one time, miſſing of a Guide, and miſtaking our Road<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we fell ſhort of any convenient Tow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or Village capable to receive us; ſo tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Sun being down, my Lord order'd one of his Servants to call <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a few ſtraggling Houſes, to ſee if they could afford us any Entertainment: The chie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of 'em appear'd to be a kind of an Inn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to that they made their firſt Addreſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Maſter, upon our calling, cam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> out in an old tatter'd Shepherd's Coat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and being dimm-ſighted, clapt his Specta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cles on his Noſe, the better to diſcer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> what we were; and ſeeing our Equ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>page above the ordinary Rank, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:153229:34"/> many obliging Scrapes and Cringes, told us his Houſe was at our Service, and we ſhould be very well entertain'd. It growing dark, my Lord accepted of his Proffer, and ſo we diſmounted: but when he perceiv'd the Hangings con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted only of Cobwebs, and the other Furniture not much unanſwerable to them, he would have been gone, had he not been aſſur'd there was no better Conveniency within Three Leagues; and the Night was not only dark, and much over-cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ded, but that by the Rain, that then began to fall in greater Showers, were promis'd greater Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences, beſides the threatned Danger of the VVay; and I being very much tired, was glad of an Opportunity to reſt me; but more over-joy'd, when I ſaw the Pot over the Fire, verily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding before, that that had been Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Night, and we muſt have gone Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perleſs to Bed, not expecting any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions in ſuch a Place, at ſuch a time of Night.</p>
               <p>Our Landlord having VVelcom'd my Lord, and his Retinue, with ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements as he had, order'd the Cloth
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:153229:35"/> immediately to be laid in the Parlour, and a great Buſtle there was in the Houſe to put Things in pimlico; when all on a ſudden my Landlady cry'd out, ſhe had not Chairs or Stools enough, and ſo ſent her Daughter to the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours a borrowing; but they being as ſlenderly provided, ſhe could procure only a Form on which they uſed to kill Hogs; and that it might come leaſt in ſight, was planted at the Lower-end of the Table, whither the Light of our one Candle ſhin'd but very faintly.</p>
               <p>For the Conveniency of our Horſes, I ſhould have told you before, the Hogs were made Cloſe-Priſoners, being crou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded together into a little Hole that uſed to ſerve for a Dog-Kennel. Theſe things appear'd a little odd, as very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſual to us; but where there is no better to be had, it is Prudence to reſt contented. And now Supper being taken up, and ſet on the Table, we were invited in; and what ſhould we find, but every one a VVooden Bowl or Diſh, with a Spoon in it of the ſame Metal, full of <hi>Ola Podrida,</hi> a kind of Pottage made of ſeveral ſorts of Herbs,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:153229:35"/> and a little Minc'd Meat to ſavour it, that our Landlord himſelf, without the help of an Herbal, could never have found 'em out, at leaſt, by their Names. My Lord, who was not uſed to ſuch Diet, and had order'd us ſtrictly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal his Quality, leſt, as is uſual, there ſhould be any Treachery in the People of the Houſe, who ſuſpecting, by that means, he had great Riches about him, might give Notice to ſome Gangs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, order'd us all to ſit down, rather to pleaſe my Hoſt and Hoſteſs, than any Stomach he had to this Firſt and Laſt Courſe; for, upon Enquiry, we found there was no Second: nor had they now had ſuch Sumptuous Dyet (as they term'd it,) but that their Daughter's Sweet-heart had made a Promiſe to come with divers Friends, and in the Morning to Marry her; but had juſt then ſent Word, and could not perform his Promiſe.</p>
               <p>We, however, having keen Appetites, eat a little; partly to ſtill the grouling of our empty Guts, and partly in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency. As for Drink, there was not any but <hi>Adam</hi>'s Ale, VVhey, and about
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:153229:36"/> two Gallons of Milk, in all the Hamlet: with the firſt and the latter mix'd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we made our Beverage; our Hoſt, his Spouſe, and Daughter, fed luſtily, and carous'd Fair-Water as ſavourly as if it had been the beſt Hock, or Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goon Such is the Advantage of Uſe to Mankind, that being accuſtom'd to a Diet, it ſuffices Nature, and become; pleaſant. The Wooden Utenſils, and the other Table-Materials, being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd, the Damſel, who was well-Complexion'd, well-Featur'd, and of a Middle Stature, taking the Sign from her Old Dad, ſung very ſweetly, and had in it much Skill and Judgment: With which, I perceiv'd, my Lord was better pleas'd, than with his Commons: I could perceive them talk with the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of her Eyes, and took an Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to whiſper ſomething into her Ear: At which ſhe ſeem'd rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyc'd, than diſpleas'd; and I have ſince been inform'd, That People, in thoſe Parts, keeping ſuch Houſes on the Road, are glad if they can Oblige a Noble Gueſt, to make him Liberal; even their Wives, if tollerably Handſom and Young,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:153229:36"/> or otherwiſe, their Daughters, will creep to Bed to them, with the leaſt Hint, it will not diſpleaſe them; and I am not miſtaken, if, I ſay, my Lord, to make the Night paſs the pleaſanter in ſo hard a Lodging, did not Tap the Veſſel her expected Bridegroom was to have Broach'd the next Morning; for I heard bare Feet come patting up Stairs when he was a Bed But leſt I prove too te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, Bed-time being come, a greater Buſtle was made; for the Houſe afforded but Three, and thoſe very ſcurvy ones, and we were Ten, beſides the Family. My Lord, we knew, expected to have one to himſelf, and another kind of a Bed-fellow (as I before hinted) than any of us. The Hoſt, his Wife and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for our better Accommodation, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerouſly offer'd, the VVeather being warm, to take up their Night's Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters on a heap of Ruſhes; and after a while, another Bed was procur'd abroad for three of our Companions; and ſo we haſted to our ſeveral Cabbins: That to which I, and two of my Companions, were deſtined, was the moſt exalted, being one degree advanc'd above the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:153229:37"/> Garret, or a Cavity between the Ridges and the Raſters, the general Randezvous of Rats and VVeeſels; to aſcend to which, we went up a Ladder but of a very few Steps; then popt thorough a Trap door, like a Play houſe Devil from under the Stage, it being a curious Inner-Room, and no Partition but the Pan-tiles between us and Heaven; and it had been better for me, that I had been a Rope-Dancer, as it fell out in the Morning. That Night, indeed, our Hoſteſs leading us, we kept our Feet regular on the Rafters, till we came where our Bed lay upon a heap of Bruſhwood, in lieu of a Bedſtead; and then leaving us a bit of Candle as long as her Noſe, with great care and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion we ſhould not be waſteful, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh it as ſoon as we were pig'd in, ſhe dropt us a Courtſie, and bolted down again as if a Ghoſt had vaniſh'd into the nether Shades; and now we had leiſure to take a further View: VVhen, upon Examination, we found the Ticking of our Bed to be an old VVool-ſack, ſtuff'd with Rags, and the Combings of Hemp, Thiſtle-Down, Hogs-Hair, and ſuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:153229:37"/> ſort of Materials; our Rug being made of Liſts, Shreds, and patch'd in divers places, conſiſted of as many va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Colours as a Herald's Coat, and challeng'd any VVoollen-Drapers Shop, for variety, to match them: Blankets we had none; but our Sheets were pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty cleanly; yet being made of Cloath a Groat a yard, were as ſoft as Hogs-Skins: Our Bolſter, indeed, was ſtuff'd with VVing and Tail-Feathers, that in Moulting-time, I ſuppoſe, had been pick'd up on the Heaths and Commons.</p>
               <p>Seeing this coarſe Entertainment, we deliberated a while, whether we had beſt unſtrip, or not; but the Weather being exceeding Hot, we, at laſt, threw off our Cloaths, and in we jumpt. We had not lain long, but whole Battalions of Fleas, and flying Squadrons of Gnats, as hungry as Cannibals, invaded us, to feed on the Plenty which Providence had ſent them. All our Hands were inſtantly at work; but we could not defend our Buttocks from the one, nor our Faces from the other of theſe Blood-thirſty Enemies: they bit, and we claw'd; I grumbl'd, and my Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:153229:38"/> ſwore. Nor were Rats, Mice and Weeſels wanting; for ever and anon they run croſs us, ſqueaking and fighting; ſo that if we had leap'd out of Bed to avoid the ſmaller Blood-ſuckers, we muſt unavoidably have taken a Dance in the Rats Morris, and hazarded more dangerous Bitings. About Two in the Morning, when we began to ſlumber a little, the feaſted Vermin giving us ſome reſpite for the Blood they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted, we were all on a ſudden ſtrangely alarm'd by an harmonious Conſort of Muſick in the Ceiling of our Bed-Chamber, (for there, it ſeems, the neighbouring Cats kept their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturnal Revels,) which continued in divers Strains for about two Hours, and then they fil'd off from their Copula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Recreation, to their Mouſe-catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Occupation.</p>
               <p>Thus we lay ſurrounded with all theſe Plagues, and under a neceſſity of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during them till the long wiſh'd-for Dawning came to relieve us from the hot Service we were engag'd in; for our little Enemies, by this time, having digeſted their firſt Banquet, came croud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:153229:38"/> again for a ſecond; ſo that before we could lift up our Hand to diſengage our Faces of the Gnats, or Muſchata's, we had fifty Fleas apiece nibbling at our Arſes.</p>
               <p>At laſt, the welcome Light ſhin'd thorough the Crannies of the ſhatter'd Walls; which we beheld with as much Joy, as one ſifted from the long du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Shackles in a dark Dungeon; or a ſtale Maid, who has drawn in a luſty young Fellow to go to Church with her in earneſt. Glad of this Deliverance, out we jumpt, as mottely as one of our Countrey Spaniels; or a young Lady newly come Abroad to Air her ſelf, after the Small-pox. But now another Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief befell me, for reeling too far before I could recover, miſſing the Joyces, treading on the Laths, down I dropt on my Lord's Head, who lay in the Room underneath, and could perceive a Thing in White vaniſh out of his Chamber, as I was falling; for the Crack, and Dropping of the Ceiling, had given ſo much Notice, that I found none in bed with him, yet never diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but he was better pleas'd with his Night's Lodging than we had been.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:153229:39"/>
               <p>At firſt he ſtarted, and ſeem'd ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſurpriz'd; but ſeeing it was I, and that I was piteouſly ſcratch'd with the ſnags of the Laths, upon my Excuſe, after having chid me for taking no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter heed, he order'd me immediately to dreſs my ſelf, and call up thoſe Servants that lay in the Lower-Room, and ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon them in the neighbouring Houſe. I punctually obeyed his Orders, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the haſtier to get to ſome good Town where we might refreſh our ſelves. He wonder'd to ſee us ſo ſpeckl'd; but look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Pocket-Glaſs, he found he had not altogether eſcap'd the Hopping Legion.</p>
               <p>We ſtay'd not for Breakfaſt, but liberally rewarding our Hoſt with Two Pieces of Eight, our Hoſteſs with one, and the pretty Daughter with another, an Eſtate in their Pockets, we mounted, and took the Road we before intended.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus I first Hardſhip felt, but not the last;</l>
                  <l>New Woes ſucceed, to plague me for Tricks past:</l>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:153229:39"/>
                  <l>Fate, at next ſtroak, ſtrikes me from Fortune's Wheel;</l>
                  <l>But ne'er alone will I her Fury feel:</l>
                  <l>Since ſhe will me a deſperate Gameſter make,</l>
                  <l>I'll play at all, but that I'll win ſome Stake:</l>
                  <l>To ſpite her, I her Fav'rites will out-wit,</l>
                  <l>And puſh them in, who dragg'd me to the Pit.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How, in their Way to <hi>Naples,</hi> they were Set-upon by divers Thieves, or <hi>Banditti,</hi> who came out of a Wood upon them; and the brave Reſiſtance they made. How his Horſe being kill'd, he fled into the Wood, and was there rifled and made Priſoner by them; his Lord, and all his Companions, that were not kill'd, beſides himſelf, charging through, and eſcaping.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>WE had not rid above a League, but being on a riſing-Ground, we had a Proſpect of a Country that
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:153229:40"/> appear'd to be more fair than any we had yet ſeen ſince our paſſing the <hi>Alps:</hi> And ſeeing a conſiderable Town, call'd — about Two Leagues, or thereabouts, farther, we concluded we ſhould meet with better Refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than we had the fore-going Night, or the preſent Morning<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And thus flattering our ſelves with a good Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, we rode on, till deſcending the Hill, we came into a Hollow-Way, the one ſide being inclos'd with a craggy ſhatter'd Hill, and the other with a large Wood, riſing conſiderably higher than the Road; we were not far enter'd into it, but we heard a Piſtol go off behind us, and immediately another be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us; when not well knowing what to make on't, we all provided againſt the worſt: Which, indeed, was bad enough; for we had no ſooner turn'd a blind of Trees, but we eſpy'd five or ſix Horſe-men, not a Bow-ſhot off, ſpreading croſs the Way; and others coming out of the Wood, at ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance beyond them. This gave Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, that they would not prove Friends; but my Lord being a Man of great
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:153229:40"/> Courage, and his eight Followers of a Daring little inferiour to his, he reſolv'd to preſs on, and venture the Brunt, if it came to the Extremity, rather than ſhun a Danger where, perhaps, there might be none, by cowardly Flight. Coming nearer, and ſeeing they gave not way, but ſtood to ſtop the Paſſage, he rid up with his Sword drawn, hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by a Chain on his Wriſt, and his Piſtol cockt, and bore it on the Pummel of his Saddle, with the Muzzle mounted, having order'd his Men to halt, demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed what they were, and why they ſtopt up the Way?</p>
               <p>They anſwer'd him ſomewhat rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>We are the</hi> Banditti, <hi>Servants to</hi> Mompazon, <hi>Chief Lord of the Road; and if you and your Companions have any regard for your Lives, it is your wiſest way, to deliver all the Treaſure you have about you, as a Tribute to our Maſter, for treſpaſſing on his Ground.</hi> My Lord ſmil'd at this, thinking, or, at leaſt, diſſembl'd he thought ſo, that they were only in Jeſt; and told them, He believ'd they were Gentlemen only upon a Frollick, and if they would accompany him to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:153229:41"/> the next Town, they ſhould be enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with the Beſt the Place would afford. To this they reply'd ſurlily, They muſt convince him by ſtronger Arguments, if he perſiſted not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver his Treaſure; and ſo having made ready, bore up to ſeize his Horſes Bridle. Upon which, perceiving they were in Earneſt, he fired, and ſhot the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt thorough the Head, ſo that down he dropt in an eternal ſlumber; the next he miſs'd, but kill'd his Horſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him: Then we haſted to his Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and fired ſo thick (I being as active at that Sport as the reſt, though I kept ſideling on) that we were, in a manner, circled in Clouds of Smoke; and made ſuch havock of our Enemy, though twice our number, that they gave ground; and we preſſing hotly on, were trained into an Ambuſh; for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately a greater number appear'd at our Backs, who firing their Carbines at a diſtance, kill'd my Horſe; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon being diſmounted, I crept into the Wood: My Lord, I perceiv'd, ſeeing himſelf in this ſtrait, with much Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution and Bravery Charg'd thorough
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:153229:41"/> thoſe that firſt encounter'd him; in which Action I ſee two of his Retinue drop, but with the reſt (<hi>Parthians</hi> like, firing behind them as they fled) got ſafe to the next Town, where the Purſuit ended, it being, as I afterwards heard, a ſtrong Place, where a Spaniſh Troop of Guards lay; who, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding my Lord's Entreaty, more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly for the recovery of me, whom he ſuppos'd they had taken Priſoner, and conſiderable Proffers, would not venture after them; ſaying, They knew they always went in ſtrong Parties, and not being certain of their Number, might be cut off by their Ambuſcades in the Woods, or Hollows of the Rocks. My Lord (as I heard at my return to <hi>France</hi>) was greatly grieved, to be thus unluckily deprived of me; but perceiving I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd the Wood, and ſuppoſing how barbarous ſoever they were, they would not kill me in cool blood, he comforted himſelf, that one day or other he might recover me, for Money, or by Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: But I never had the happineſs to ſee him more.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:153229:42"/>
               <p>The Purſuit over, ſome of them came back to the Place of Skirmiſh, to carry off their Companions; when two or three ſcouting into the Buſhes and Shrubs, to ſee if we had thrown any any of our Treaſure there, though I lay as ſnug in a Thicket as cou'd be, till I thought all might be blown over, one of them, ne'ercheleſs, 'ſpied my Heels; for I like a fooliſh Baſtard, ſuppoſing all was hid, becauſe my Head was) found I was ſeiz'd by a ſtrong Hand, and dragg'd out. Being thus took napping, I thought it the beſt way to fall on my Knees, and beg Mercy. At firſt, they threatned me with many bloody Oaths, and direful Imprecations, ſetting their Swords to my Breaſt, ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they would kill me, unleſs I would diſcover how many more of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany was abſconded? or what Treaſure we had hid there, before they came up with us? But when I pull'd out all the Gold and Silver, except eight Piſtoles quilted in my Shirt-Collar, they begun to unwrinkle their Brows; and ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but finding no more, they gave car to my Proteſtations, That there
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:153229:42"/> was no more of our Company in the Wood, but my ſelf, nor any Treaſure beſides what I had given them; and ſo ordering me, on pein of Death, not to make a word of any Money to their Companions, they mounted me behind one of them, and convoy'd me to the Main Gang; where the ſubſtitute Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, impower'd with the Command of the Party, by his Chieftain, in this Day's Adventure, ſeeing me finely cloathed, and of a very fair Complexion, and that my Anſwers to his Demands were above the Ordinary Rank, of my Years, he concluded me to be of Quality; and therefore expecting a large Ranſom, ſent me Priſoner, under the Conduct of Two of his Gang; tho' I proteſted I was but a poor Servant, and falling on my Knees, with Tears in my Eyes, begg'd he would give me liberty, that I, if poſſible, might follow and find out my Maſter:</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>But Fate deny'd me, till I found a way</l>
                  <l>For my Eſcape, far greater Pranks to play.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:153229:43"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How he was carry'd Priſoner to the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Cave where theſe Thieves had their Reſidence, cut out of a Rock in a Woody Mountain. The Deſcription he gives of it, and what he obſerved there. Of the unmerciful Uſage he at first ſuffer'd among them. Their Oath, or Articles of Combination; and manner of living.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>MY unwelcom Italian Conductors immediately poſted away with me I knew not whither, paſſing tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Woods, winding Lanes, and divers bye Paſſages, till we came to a Woody Mountain a great way from the Place where they took me up: But I, as nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly as I could, obſerved every Turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and all the Remarkable Things in our Journey, hoping, one time or other, they would turn to my advantage, in furthering my Eſcape, if I was not faln into the Hands of Cannibals, who would roaſt me like a <hi>barthol'mew-</hi>Pig, and devour me as a Dainty they had not
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:153229:43"/> lately lighted on. Well (to be brief) coming to this Mountain, Perriwig'd with over-grown Trees, after we had aſcended about Half a Furlong, with little or no great difficulty, except the various Windings, upon the removal of ſome Buſhes, as I thought, appearing then very green and pleaſant, as if they naturally grew: And turning of a Key, the Entrance of a Cave appear'd, ſo wide, that in we went, Horſe and Men: The Door, on which they were, duly artificially faſten'd, to renew the decay'd ones, and prevent Diſcovery, turning upon Hinges fix'd in the Rock, clapt after us; but ſo ſoftly, that it could not be heard twenty Paces. Into this Place came Light many ways, thorough Buſhes and Shrubs that grew over it, though very much like that we call a Twy-light, in a gray Morning: yet I could ſee, when we diſmounted, ſeveral Stables very regular; and in them, a great many very curious Horſes, well ſtor'd with Provender. They having rank'd their Steads among the reſt, one of them led me beyond theſe ſubterranean Stables, where a more comfortable Light
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:153229:44"/> appeared: when aſcending a few Steps, cut out by Art in the Rock, as I ſuppoſe the Cave had been, we came into a kind of ſtately Houſe; which made me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, by what I ſaw there, if the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory I had read of <hi>Knight-Errantry,</hi> were not <hi>Aeſop</hi>'s <hi>Fables,</hi> I was got into an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanted Caſtle; for there I beheld a great deal of Arms and Armour (this being much lighter than the Stables,) as alſo rich Apparel hanging upon Pins in the Wall; and divers Inchanted Knights, as I took them to be, ſleeping upon Ruſh-Mats and Couches.</p>
               <p>I had a great Deſire to be asking Queſtions; but being in the Hands of an Enemy, I knew not how they might be taken, and therefore remained ſilent, till I ſhould underſtand their Humours better. Paſſing this kind of a Hall, I came into their Kitchen, (for ſo I took it to be, ſeeing the She Cook's hard ſweating at the Fire, preparing Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, both Boil'd and Roaſt, againſt the coming Home of her Maſters.)</p>
               <p>Hopes of ſome Victuals, a little com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted me; for now I had been a great while without any thing to the purpoſe,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:153229:44"/> being, as ſome ſay (if it may not be taken for a Bull) Full of Emptineſs: but I grew melancholy, when I was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d into the Hands of this ſtrapping Female, with Command, That ſhe ſhould lock me up in a cloſe Room, till the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain's Orders were further known<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> My Entreaty ſignify'd no more than a Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nileſs Wretch's to a Serjeant; for in I was puſh'd, and the Key turn'd upon me. I found the Place wherein I was inclos'd to be very dark and loneſom, and fancy'd with my ſelf, that like <hi>Ulyſſes,</hi> I was now got into the <hi>Pole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phems</hi> Cave; and ſo ſtrongly, through Fear and Surprize, my Imagination worked, that Fear made me doubt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their Spits and Cauldrons were not loaded and ſtuff'd with Humane Fleſh; for thogh my Eyes, in part, gave Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to the contrary, yet I found ſome difficulty to credit 'em: and what more heightned my Suſpicion, I heard, as I conjectur'd, piteous Sighs and Groans in a diſtant Apartment, as of a miſerable Perſon in great Diſtreſs; which caſt me into ſuch a Fit of a Trembling, that my Knees knockt together like the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:153229:45"/> ratling Branches of a naked Tree, when beaten againſt each other by fierce <hi>March</hi> Winds. And in this plight I continu'd, groaping up and down for ſome Hours, when I heard without, a very great Trampling, and many Sounds of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Voices; and ſoon after, a Key turn'd in the Door, and I was order'd by my Female Jaylor to advance, for the Great Captain. <hi>Mompazon,</hi> was arriv'd, and deſir'd to ſee him.</p>
               <p>Upon this, I recollected, as well as Fear would give me leave, my dejected Spirits; and coming into the Hall, I found him ſitting at the Table, in State: His Grim Countenance, Swarthy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, and huge Long Whiskers, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented him ſo terrible to me, that I concluded him no other than a ſecond <hi>Cerberus,</hi> the fabled Porter to <hi>Pluto,</hi> King of the Infernal Regions: His Voice, when he ask'd me divers Queſtions, who I was? who were my Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions? and whence we came? ſounded like a Speaking-Trumpet, or the Roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Lion: His Sword, that lay on the Table before him, was at leaſt Four Inches Broad, and Four Foot Long. To
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:153229:45"/> what he ask'd me, I anſwer'd him as well as my abrupt Stammerings, occaſion'd by Fear, would give me leave. But not ſatisfied, but that I was of Quality, he order'd me to the Pully, to extort from me what he thought I conceal'd; then had I a Cord faſten'd about my Thumbs, and great Weights faſten'd at my Heels; and in this manner being drawn up, I hung ſo long, that I thought my Legs and Arms would have parted from my Body: then, in that Poſture, was I or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd, by reaſon of my tender Age, to have my Buttocks exercis'd with ſix Strings of knotted Whip-Cord at the End of a Stick, which, I was afterwards inform'd, others uſed to have on their Backs with Wyer, and afterwards rubb'd over with Gun-Powder. But as mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful as they were to me, by omitting the two latter, I conceited, all my Old School-Maſter had given me, was but a Flea-biting to this; and thought that his departed Ghoſt, in Revenge, had inſtill'd this barbarous Cruelty into their Minds, to revenge, in ſome meaſure, the Injuries I had done him; or that the Prieſt's Curſes had reach'd me: But my
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:153229:46"/> piteous Cryes and Entreaties, at length, made the Barbarians relent: And being taken down, unable to ſtand, leſt I ſhould die of my Uſage, I was put to Bed, where my Breech ſtuck to my Shirt and the Sheets like Birdlime; and only that Evening I had a little warm Broth given me, and a Glaſs of Wine, of which their Cave was well ſtor'd, taken from Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, as Free-Plunder upon the Road.</p>
               <p>As I lay in Bed, I heard the grim Captain ſay, <hi>Come, Puniſh him no more, lest he die, and we loſe our expected Ranſom;</hi> but ſpeaking to their Female Attendant, commanded her to give me the liberty of the Kitchen and Hall, but no farther, and ſee what ſhe could wheedle out of me by fair Means, and good Uſage. Having feaſted and drunk plentifully, they laid them down to ſleep; till juſt before Day, upon the tinkling of a little Bell, they got up, and went to their old Trade, with all their Strength, as having Notice the Evening before, by one of their Scouts, That a Rich Convoy was to come from <hi>Naples,</hi> in order to paſs for <hi>Rome.</hi> Leaving only their Female Houſe-Keeper, two Grooms, and a
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:153229:46"/> Porter of the Gate at home, ſhe came to my Bed-ſide, and ſeeming greatly to pity the Severity I had undergone, brought with her a Flask of <hi>Florence</hi> Wine; which was more welcome than her Preſence: having drank a Glaſs, or two, and revived me a little, ſhe helped me to riſe, and ſet a Gold Chicken before me, for my Breakfaſt, bidding me be of Good-chear; for though ſhe believ'd I wou'd be kept Priſoner there all my Life-time, for ought ſhe knew, if Money was not ſent for my Ranſom, yet ſhe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured me, my Puniſhment, as to any thing to be corporally inflicted on me, was paſt. At this I appeared wonderfully dejected, and entreated her to become an humble Interceſſor for me, that I might be diſmiſs'd, ſeeing I being of poor Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and only a Servant in that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany where they found me, could never expect any Ranſom; my Father, for ſomething I had ſpoke that diſpleaſed him, having utterly renounc'd me, and would rather, if he knew it, rejoyce in my Miſery, than in my Releaſe. She told me, ſhe durſt not move any thing that way in my Behalf, and therefore
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:153229:47"/> bid me be content with my Condition, and leave the reſt to Time; and ſo leaving me penſive and ſad, went about her Houſhold Affairs. In the mean while, having ſatiated my craving Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach with the beſt Morſel <hi>Italy</hi> had af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded me ſince my coming into it, which I wiſh'd I never had ſeen, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity led me to take a ſtricter View of the Place, and meditate on my Eſcape.</p>
               <p>Having caſt my on divers Things, at laſt I fix'd them on the Orders of this wicked Crew, hung up on a Pillar, Sworn to, and Subſcribed with their Names; which denoted no leſs than One hundred and Twenty in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination, and for Curioſity-ſake, I wrote them down: <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>I. I <hi>A. B.</hi> Swear by the Head and Soul of our Captain, to be O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to all his Commands.</item>
                  <item>II. To be Faithful to my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions in all their Deſigns and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts.</item>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:153229:47"/>
                  <item>III. To be always preſent at ſuch Meetings as the Captain ſhall appoint, here, or in any other Place, except his leave to the contrary.</item>
                  <item>IV. To be ready at all hour, by Day and by Night, upon Call or Notice.</item>
                  <item>V. Never to deſert my Companions in any Danger, or otherwiſe, to the laſt Breath.</item>
                  <item>VI. Never to flie from an equal number of Oppoſers, but rather die, couragiouſly fighting on the Place.</item>
                  <item>VII. To Help one another, whether Taken, Impriſon'd, in Sickneſs, or any other Diſtreſs.</item>
                  <item>VIII. Never to leave, if poſſible I can bring it off, any of my Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions Bodies, wounded or dead, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind me, to fall into the Enemy's Hands.</item>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:153229:48"/>
                  <item>IX. To Confeſs nothing, if Taken; or ever to Diſcover the Abodes and Reſidence of my Accomplices, though put to Racks, Tortures, or Death it ſelf. And this Oath when I Break in the leaſt Tittle, may Power and Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be here and hereafter my Plague and Puniſhment.</item>
               </list>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus Vice do's oft a Combination find,</l>
                  <l>Stricter than the now in faſhion, Vertue, binds:</l>
                  <l>My Projects though to 'ſcape this Crew, must deep</l>
                  <l>Be laid; my Wits must not be now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep:</l>
                  <l>This kind of Living, nothing ſuits my Vein;</l>
                  <l>I must be freed, and Rambling once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:153229:48"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How he meditates his Eſcape and Revenge: Finds there a Beautiful Captive: And hears the Woman that Dreſs'd the Thieves Victuals, and look'd-after their Den, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the Comical Hiſtory of her Life, and Manner of coming thither. How he wonderfully eſcap'd; and cauſing the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of this Nest of Thieves, releaſed the ſorrowful Lady.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THrough Fear of Danger, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire once more to ſee my Native Countrey, my Mind run extremely on Projects, how I might Out-wit theſe Blood-ſucking, Crafty Vermine, and bring a Miſchief on their Heads, as ſuch Spoilers deſerve, whoſe Hands are againſt all Perſons; and the Hands of all Men, for the General Safety, ought to be againſt them. Theſe, at this time, were my Thoughts; though, indeed, I have ſince, in ſome meaſure, Out-done the moſt Expert of them. Having caſt many things in my Mind, I was fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:153229:49"/> at a loſs; but at laſt, reſolved to ſee what I could do with our bouncing Female: And inſtead of her Wheedling me, I concluded to ſummon all my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity to Out-doe her. But how, handſomly, to break the Ice (as the Countrey-man calls it) and ſtart what might be moſt Taking, was the main Matter: Sometimes I fancy'd to tell her what great Matters I would procure her, if ſhe would further my Eſcape, and go along with me into my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey: But that was daſh'd again, when I conſider'd, her main Diſcourſe tended to that, by the Captain's Order; and that it would, if ſhe ſhould be falſe to me, improve my Puniſhment, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long my Impriſonment. Whilſt I was thus muſing about what I ſhould do, ſhe having made an end of her Work, came to me, leading a very Fair, but Dejected fellow-Priſoner in her Hand, on whoſe Beauty Sorrow had implanted Paleneſs, and her Cheeks ſeem'd furrow'd with the often trickling of Tears. After a Sigh or two, ſhe ſate down by me: And our Two-handed Houſe-keeper, to divert the Melancholy ſhe perceiv'd had
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:153229:49"/> ſeiz'd us, propos'd to give us a brief Narration of her Pranks, and how ſhe came to this Place, Truſt, and Office. Which ſeeing us attentive to liſten to, ſhe began in this manner:</p>
               <p>IT matters not (ſaid ſhe) to tell you where I was born, it being too great a Difficulty for me to do, ſeing my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents were Wandring Strolers, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried me at their Backs thorough ſo many Countreys, before I came to Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that themſelves could never give me any direct Account of it; only thus far, That the Chamber where my Mother Pigg'd me, was a Gravel-Pit; her Bed, a few Ruſhes on the Ground; Curtains, Pebble-Stones; and Teſter, the Skyes: And at Twelve Years of Age I had the wide World to ſhift in; my Parents taking their leave of me, after ſome little ſwinging on Croſs-Timber, for Breaking-open and Robbing a Houſe, and Murthering moſt of the Family.</p>
               <p>The Terrour of this Diſaſter, and my Averſion to the kind of Living wherein they had hitherto dragg'd me up, made me conſider how, by ſome
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:153229:50"/> genteeler way, I might advance my Youth, and that little Beauty that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had furniſh'd me withal. Seeing others Fine, I emulated their Bravery, being homely Clad my ſelf, and much affected Gaudy Apparel, yet was a great Hater of Labour and Pains-taking; and hearing what a Brave Place <hi>Naples</hi> was, and the Gallantry of thoſe People that liv'd there, I reſolv'd to trudge thither, in hopes of mending my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and bettering my Fortunes: And ſo ſetting out, without any further Deliberation, and almoſt at every other ſtep ſtruck Fire on the Flint-paved Cauſeways; an Emblem of what Fire-works I ſhould make before my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.</p>
               <p>Coming into this ſtately City, the moſt ſpacious in all <hi>Italy,</hi> except <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Venice,</hi> I wander'd up and down, begging from Door to Door, for ſeveral Days; till an Old Woman who kept an Ordinary, ſeeing me a likely Girl, and ſhe then wanting a Scullion Drudge, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd me as her Servant. But this kind of Work not ſuiting my Humour, I ſtay'd no longer then I could make a
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:153229:50"/> Booty; and then packing up my Awls, gave her the Go-by. I found, by our Trade, ſhe had Money, though, for fear of loſing it, ſhe always complain'd of Poverty; but where it was neſted, and how to find and take theſe White and Yellow Birds, I was at a loſs; till one day, muſing on the Matter, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to fire the Callico-Hangings in her Chamber, as done by Accident of a Candle placed too near them, when I light her to Bed. This I effected; and ſhe thereupon, the firſt thing ſhe did, leaving me labouring to extinguiſh the Flame, which I eaſily ſubdued, was running into a little dark Cloſet, and lifting up a Board, ſo artificially plac'd, as if it had been as firmly nail'd down as the reſt, took out ſomething, on which, no doubt, her Heart was moſt Intent; and that, I concluded muſt be her Treaſure.</p>
               <p>I had ſoon put out the Fire; and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to her, ſaid, <hi>Pray, Seniora</hi> (or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs) <hi>don't be frighted; the Danger is over.</hi> But inſtead of Thanking me, though I look'd, with Smoke and Soot, like a Brimſtone-Devil, recollecting her A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:153229:51"/> and Affright, Anger took place; ſo that falling on me with great fury, ſhe cufft and kickt me well-favour'd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for my Careleſsneſs (as ſhe term'd it.) I bore it patiently, however, as knowing now I had not long to ſtay with her; for the next day, when the Houſe was full of People, and all in a Hurry, I ſtole her Bunch of Keys out of the Barr, ſneak'd up Stairs, unhoarded the long im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon'd Caſh, and ſo rubb'd-off, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ceremonious Complement at parting: For the loſs of which (as I was afterwards inform'd) ſhe fell Diſtracted, and took up her Quarters in the College of the Bethlemites.</p>
               <p>Having got what I long'd for, and taken on content, I trudg'd on all that Day, and all the Night following, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough all the Croſs-Ways I could find, for fear of a Purſuit: but when the next Morning-Sun gilded the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain-tops with its chearful Beams, I found my ſelf weary and faint, through long Travel, and want of Food; when ſtriking about a Furlong into a large Wood, I took the boldneſs (after having a little ſatisfy'd my craving Stomach
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:153229:51"/> with Kernels, Medlers, and other wild Fruit growing there, and a Promiſe of better Fare) to open my Pouch, and found Coin, the Richeſt of both ſorts, amounting in all to Forty Ducats; a greater Summ, perhaps, than many of my Anceſtors had ſeen of their own, in the whole progreſs of their Lives. This exceedingly lightned my Heart, till Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother's Cataſtrophie bolting into my Thoughts, cauſed in me ſome Allay; and put it into my Head, that I was not yet arriv'd at a place of Safety: ſo tucking up my Treaſure in an old ragged Petticoat, I again took the Road, begging and taking up my Nights Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in Woods and Barns, for fear my Changing of Money in thoſe Parts, ſhould breed Suſpicion, and cauſe my being ſtayed; till I came into the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burbs of the City of <hi>Florence,</hi> and there I concluded I was pretty ſafe. This City gives Name to the Province or Dukedom of <hi>Florence,</hi> and is a very fair one, feated near the River <hi>Arne</hi> and <hi>Chian,</hi> beautified with many ſtately E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difices; the Duke being accounted the Richeſt and Chiefeſt Merchant in <hi>Italy,</hi>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:153229:52"/> uſually call'd the <hi>Great Duke of</hi> Tuſcany. Here I bought me a convenient neat Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and going into the Fields, ſtript me of my coarſe Apparel, almoſt dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated into Rags, and bury'd them in a Lime-Pit, that they ſhould never riſe up to accuſe me, by any Deſcription that might be given concerning them. This done, and being a little ſmugg'd up, I came back again, and bought other Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries I wanted; and about the Sun's declining, I took me a Lodging, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending many ſham-Occaſions of my coming thither, as, That I had a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther return'd thither, on board the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys that had been cruiſing in the <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terranean,</hi> &amp;c. But at laſt, finding my Landlady an honeſt, free, open-hearted Old Woman, but withal very poor, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having taken a View of that ſpacious and pleaſant City, taking its Name from the curious Gardens of Flowers that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt every where incompaſs it, I told her, I was ſo mainly taken with its Situa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Healthful Air, that I would, if I could meet with a convenient Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, ſettle there; and if ſhe would uſe her Endeavour to that purpoſe, I would,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:153229:52"/> out of the little Money I had, give her a Gratuity; and better it, when more able. She promis'd me, her Diligence ſhould not be wanting to ſerve me: When, to encourage her, I ſent for a good Supper, and a Can of Wine; and ſo we ſpent the Evening in Telling of Old Stories. In the Morning, ſhe went upon the Hunt; and returning about noon, told me, ſhe had been ſucceſsful; for that a rich Merchant's Maid died the Day before, and they were deſtitute of another. After Dinner, I went to this Place; and though but young in Years, was very well Approv'd of; my Face, and the little Replies I made hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening to be very Taking with my Maſter and Miſtreſs; but more (as I perceiv'd by his Smiles and Leering) with a Young Spark that ſtood at their Elbow; with whom I afterwards was better acquainted, though he had better never have ſeen me, as in the Sequel will appear. To be brief then, I was Hired, and admitted one of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticks.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:153229:53"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>She continues her Story; How being in the Service of a Rich Merchant of <hi>Florence,</hi> the Caſh-keeper fell in Love with her, promis'd her Marriage, and made her Rich Preſents. How ſhe diſcover'd her Maſter's Intreagues with his Part'ner's Wife. And how her Sweet-heart, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaking her Bed, ſtumbl'd into that of her Miſtreſs; and of the Adventure that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell him there, and how ſhe reſented ſo great an Affront put upon her.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>BEing initiated one of the Family, I was, no doubt, in a happy Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if I could have ſeen when I was well. At firſt I liv'd very comfortably, making it my buſineſs to pleaſe and wind my ſelf into the good Opinion of All, ſoon perfectly underſtanding the Ways of the Houſe, and in a Year's-time became Head Maid, or rather Houſe-keeper: At what time, another Merchant, ſomewhat in Years, who had marry'd a Beautiful Young Lady, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:153229:53"/> Part'ner with my Maſter; and and brought his Family, which was but ſmall, to our Habitation: By which means my Vails and Wages much encreaſed; and with them, likewiſe my Pride. So that affecting Gaity, I lay'd out laviſhly, till at laſt I appear'd ſo Lovely in the Caſhier's Eyes, <hi>viz.</hi> the Young Spark before-mention'd, that he took all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient Opportunities to do me Favours. I diſſembl'd my taking Notice of them, till at length, by my amorous Leers, Winks, Smiles, and other Geſtures, I had drawn him in over Head and Ears in Love with me; thinking no Treats nor Preſents within his Power, that I could reaſonably demand, too much for me. So having nooz'd the Woodcock with the Snares of my Glances, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to make the beſt Market of him. He ſued earneſtly for a Night's Endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in my Charming and Raviſhing Arms and Embraces (as he was pleas'd to ſtile 'em.) But tho' I gave him no abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Denial, I found Excuſes and Delays, when I perceiv'd him moſt preſſing towards, and languiſhing for Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, till I had made him pay as
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:153229:54"/> coſtly for it, as if he had Intreagu'd with a Dutcheſs</p>
               <p>I ſoon brought him to this, when he perceiv'd other Arguments were in vain: Rings, and Jewels, and what he thought moſt tempting, he procured me: And for thoſe precious Preſents, thought himſelf over-recompens'd with a few Smiles, and my kind Acceptance. At this Diſtance I held him a conſiderable Time, till hearing a Rich Uncle of his died, and left him a good Eſtate, and then I thought it my time to cloſe with him, and hamper the Woodcock in a Matrimonial Sprindge. I took my time to propoſe it to him, when the warm Touches of my Naked Breaſts, and warmer Kiſſes, had heightned and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired beyond an ordinary Tranſport; ſtrengthning my Allegations with Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty and Bluſhes, making him believe I was Worthily deſcended, though Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune had thrown my Family from the Precipice of a great Eſtate, into the low Valley of Meanneſs and Poverty. To this Propoſal I found him but Gold in his Replies; which made me fling out of his Arms in a great Pet, and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:153229:54"/> vow ne'er to entertain any good Thoughts of him more, ſeeing his Paſſion tended only to baſe and ſiniſter Ends. He not being able to part with me, pull'd me back again; and on his Knees beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging my Pardon, proteſted to yield to whatever I deſir'd, and ſubmit himſelf, in a blind Obedience, to what I ſhould direct, without any Scruple or Relu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctancy. I then propos'd the Day of Marriage; but he ſeemed ſo-impatient of Enjoying me, that upon his ſwearing to keep the Day prefix'd punctually, for the joining our Hands, I promis'd a Surrender of the Treaſure he languiſh'd for, that very Night, and ſet the Hour for more privacy, when he ſhould ſteal into my Arms, when in Bed. At which, giving me an hundred endearing Kiſſes, he ſeemed ſo raviſh'd and tranſported, he know not how to expreſs ſufficient Thanks for my obliging Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>At the time of this Aſſignation, my Maſter's Part'ner, Signior <hi>Elnorea,</hi> was gone a Journey, and had left his Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Young Wife to the Care of <hi>Almanda,</hi> my Maſter, whoſe Fidelity he no ways
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:153229:55"/> miſtruſted: But, on the contrary, his Fair Charge had ſo overcome and cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated him, that he ſought all manner of ways to enjoy her. She repulſed the firſt Aſſaults with many Reaſons, why ſhe ought not to conſent; but at the ſecond, or more furious than the former, coming to a Capitulation, ſhe promis'd, between a kind of willing and unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to ſurrender up, that Night, the Fort of her Chaſtity, if he could hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomly give his Wife the ſlip, and convey himſelf into her Chamber, without any Suſpicion tending to a Diſcovery; for ſhe was, it ſeems, more careful of her Honour, than her Vertue. This double Appointment made, the Hours ſeemed tedious; and we fancy'd the Sun had wander'd out of its wonted Road, and gone the fartheſt way about to the Weſtern Ocean. At laſt Night came, and Supper being on the Table, I and my Spark gave our Attendance; but ſcarce could I contain, with holding my Sides, and biting my Tongue, from burſting into Laughter, when I ſee him ſtand like the Picture of the Man in the Moon, either gazing on me, or wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:153229:55"/> he knew not whither, his Wits, no doubt, being in the Eclyptick, and his Imagination bent on the ſweet Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of thoſe charming Delights and Pleaſures he ſuddenly expected to find in my ſweet and delicious Embraces; ſo that he was no further ſerviceable in his Attendance, than to make the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany Paſtime: for if his Maſter call'd for Beer, he brought him a Clean Plate; or his Miſtreſs for a Glaſs of Wine, he preſented it to me; or, to mend the Miſtake, to Madam <hi>Elnorea:</hi> which caus'd a great deal of pleaſant Diſcourſe, what ſhould be the Cauſe of this ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Diſorder?</p>
               <p>This, I obſerved, was not the Diſorder of my Spark alone; for my Maſter, by the ſtrength of Imagination, and partly by thoſe Flames the incomparable Beauty and obliging Promiſes his Part'ner's Wife had kindled in him, made him ready to diſſolve, as Snow againſt the Heat of the Sun: Fancy mov'd him to think he was already incircl'd in her ſoft Arms; and clung as cloſe in the amorous Folds of Love, as the Ivy to the begirted Oak: ſometimes he imagin'd he heard the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:153229:56"/> Twang of her harmonious Lace-Tags againſt her Stays, making her ſelf Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, to be the more ready for the ſoft Combat; and grew ſo impatient of Delay, that counterfeiting Drouſineſs, and early Buſineſs in the Morning, all things were taken away, and he haſted to Bed with his Wife the ſooner, to lull her aſleep, and ſteal away into Madam <hi>Elnorea</hi>'s Arms. He effected (as I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward underſtood) the firſt, by feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to fall into a profound ſleep, as ſoon as he was a Bed, thereby preventing the Love-toying wont to paſs between them, that he might the ſooner receive them with more Satisfaction from another. This Neglect of her Youth and Beauty, made my Miſtreſs ſhed ſome Tears, for the ſlight Regard had to her; but know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how humourſome and peeviſh he was, if ſuddenly 'waked, ſhe conſider'd, it would be more ſeaſonable to expect his Kindneſs at another time; and ſo huſhing her Cares, ſettled her ſelf to ſleep likewiſe.</p>
               <p>The cunning Husband was diligent in waiting for that Opportunity; and very carefully ſtealing out, went as ſoftly to
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:153229:56"/> the Chamber of Aſſignation; to which there was no other way, but by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment where I lay; and being wake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, in Expectation of my Spark, a Mouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tread could not 'ſcape my hearing his tripping up gingerly one Pair of Stairs above me, fancying it was my Husband-elect, who, blinded with Love, or the Darkneſs of the Night, had miſtaken his Way, and ſo expected his return, when he had groaped himſelf into a better In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; but his ſtay, and the long ſilence that enſued, made me grow both jealous of a greater Beauty than my own, whom I ſuppoſed had tempted him from me, and of being now delayed, when I had fully framed my Mind to a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency: But alas, my Love was mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken in another Place; for about Half an Hour after this diſloyal Husband had left the warm Bed of his hitherto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Bed-fellow, to go a Catterwawl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Mine, who was aged about Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and a brisk, luſty, handſom Fellow, got out of his Bed, having ſlept againſt his will; and not knowing how much of the Night had ſtoln from him, in his ſlumbering, rubbing his Eyes, between
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:153229:57"/> ſleeping and waking, groaped the way in the dark to find my Chamber; but inſtead thereof, enter'd into that of his Miſtreſs; and encountering with a Bed, doubted not but he was right: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, lifting up the Cloaths ſoftly, he laid himſelf down by her Side; and was not long there, e're he began to buſtle: which ſoon waked his Miſtreſs; who ſuppoſing it her Husband, embrac'd him with ardent Affection, crying, in a ſoft loving Tone, <hi>Oh, how Cold you are, my Dear? Come, let me warm thee in my Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces!</hi> And hugging him very cloſe, with many Kiſſes, and amorous Twi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, ſhe told him ſhe was glad what had perplex'd her in her ſleep, was but a Dream, for that ſhe fancy'd ſhe had felt for him before, all over the Bed, and and he was no way to be found; intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to tell him how ſhe had dream'd, That at that very juncture, her Man and her Maid, meaning me, were naught together, and juſt in Love's lawleſs Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>junction; but glad I am (continu'd ſhe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that it is but a Dream, and that waking<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I have thee in my Arms.</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:153229:57"/>
               <p>Theſe Actions and Expreſſions not only convinced my Spark he was in an Error, but ſo ſtartl'd and ſurpriz'd him, that he knew not what to think or do; at firſt he was almoſt dead with fear, but by degrees recollecting his ſcatter'd Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, he bethought himſelf of a Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem to protect him from Diſcovery: All the Paſſages he had obſerved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween his Maſter and Partner's Wife came freſh into his Memory, and from all the Circumſtances concluded they were in this critical Minute conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their Loves, and that if he refrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from ſpeaking, he doubted not but ſhe falling a-ſleep again, he might ſteal away, and haſten to my more deſired Embraces: But, alas! in this he found himſelf deceived; for the Fancies in her Dream, and her natural Inclination, had ſo warmed her Blood, that abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for that time the Modeſty of her Sex, ſhe grew ſo impatient of Delays, that he found himſelf incapable of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting the Emotions ſhe had raiſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him, but ſuffered himſelf to be taught by her thoſe Love-Leſſons deſign'd him by another School-Miſtreſs. She found
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:153229:58"/> him ſo active and vigorous in his Careſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Embraces, above what are uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually the Attendants of a Marriage-Bed, that, together with his continued ſilence, gave her a ſuſpition that ſhe was miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in her Bedfellow; whilſt he, on the other hand, lay ſweating and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling in a peck of Troubles how to make his Retreat handſomely before his Maſter's Return: For if he ſurpriz'd him, he could expect nothing but a bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Revenge for what he had acted to his Diſhonour and Diſgrace, through miſtake.</p>
               <p>After a Thouſand Cogitations and Revolvings in his Mind, weighing each Particular in the Ballance of his green Underſtanding, he conſider'd it might be of dangerous Conſequence to ask Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of the injur'd Lady for what had paſſed between them; and again, to ſteal away when ſhe was aſleep, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſcovering, would undoubtedly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray the whole Matter by her petulency<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or ſome little toying and wanton Diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>courſe that might ariſe upon the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band's coming; and who knows but ſhe might too amply acknowledge his Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:153229:58"/> for his late ſuppoſed Work of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pererogation, which might give him a juſt ground to believe ſome other had ſupplied his Place in his abſence, and conſequently his Man, for no other could be ſuſpected in the Family.</p>
               <p>Apprehenſions of Danger from the Diſcovery of a Secret of this great Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, put him into ſuch a Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that it was not to be judged which exceeded, the Pleaſure he had enjoyed, or the Trouble and Fear he underwent to purchaſe it. Whilſt his Thoughts were engaged in this Perplexity, a lucky one came into his Noddle, which, in all probability, might remedy all, and ſo after an endearing Kiſs or two, thus broke ſilence:</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline">'Prithee, my Dear, what didſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ou mean by that Dream thou told'ſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>en I firſt came to Bed; the Matter I va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue not, but 'tis the manner of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation that troubles me, beca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> in it thou nameſt me as thy Servant, which is more like the Language of my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs than of my dear Love. I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to be thy Husband, and will not fail, at the time appointed, to bind the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:153229:59"/> Contract with my Hand, which my Heart has already ſealed; and now I have named my Miſtreſs, ſhe, no doubt, poor innocent Lady, lies faſt a-ſleep, whilſt her perfidious Husband is in the heighth of Enjoyment with his abſent Partner's Wife.</q> And here he ended with renewed Kiſſes; but ſhe ſtarted, trembled, and turned away, not able, at preſent to make any Reply. Never was <hi>Alcmene</hi> of old ſo amazed and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized, when <hi>Jupiter</hi> had enjoyed her in the Shape of <hi>Amphitrio</hi> her Husband. The Curtain of the Night indeed hid the Confuſion of her Bluſhes and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, which elſe had appeared greater than can be reaſonably expreſſed: But ſeeing there was no Remedy to retrieve ſo ſtrange an Accident, which had at this time unwittingly broke her Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age Vow, ſhe comforted her ſelf, in that the F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lt, if any, was not deſign'd by her, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t all the Guilt ought to lye on her faithleſs Husband, who had deſerted her Bed for the lawleſs Pleaſures of an other's.</p>
               <p>She was ſomewhat loath, however, to part with the Company of her Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellow,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:153229:59"/> but Reaſon perſwaded her to it for the avoiding Danger. Wherefore taking a Diamond Ring, ſhe clapt it into the Hand of my Spark, ſaying, in a very low Voice, <hi>If you are diſcreet, hug your good Fortune in ſilence; otherwiſe you ſhall find a Reward to this Surprize and your babling Folly.</hi> Hereupon, without reply, he ſneaked away to his own Bed, whilſt I lay in vain expecting his coming to mine, miſtruſting ſome ſuch thing, but not knowing where it happened, till he gave me ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the full Relation, as it is here ſet down; which Diſappointment put me upon Revenge, which fell ſure, though ſlow in Execution: For as the Poet ſays,</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Woman, when croſt in her deſired End</l>
                  <l>Of Love, or call it Luſt, becomes a Fiend,</l>
                  <l>Till her Revenge deſtroys her deareſt Friend.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:153229:60"/>
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>She relates how her Maſter was ſurpriz'd in Bed with his Partner's Wife, upon his unexpected coming home; and what Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems were uſed by the Wife to deceive the Husband. How ſhe 'frighted her Maſter in his Return, by ſiezing him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of her Lover; with the Diſcourſe that happened between them. How ſhe, by diſcovering theſe Intriegues, ruined not only the Caſhier, but the whole Family, yet greatly inriched her ſelf; afterwards Marrying. By what means ſhe fell into the Hands of the Thieves.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>SHe would have ended her Story here at this time, reſerving the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for a more fitter opportunity; but by my Importunity ſhe thus proceeded:</p>
               <p>My Maſter (ſaid ſhe) having gained a ſpeedy Admittance, we may well ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine employed his time to the end for which that Aſſignation was made: It is needleſs, if I had been then their Bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:153229:60"/> to give an Account of every amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Folly that the Two Lovers were guilty of, which conſiſted, no doubt, more of Action than Expreſſion; and no wonder, ſince Kiſſes barrocade their Speech, we may imagine, that their Lips being tired, they encounter'd in another manner, ſomewhat more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. But in the heighth of theſe raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Enjoyments, and ſtolen Pleaſures, the amorous Lady's Husband unexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctedly came home, and having a Key to the Back-door went directly to his Chamber, having ſtruck a Light, and carry'd up with him a Candle. His un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected knocking at the Door ſtartled our Two Lovers, then more ſtrictly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangl'd in each others Arms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> than <hi>Mars</hi> was by <hi>Vulcan</hi>'s crafty Net, when intwin'd in amorous Folds with the Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian Goddeſs. But ſhe being otherwiſe employed than to come out of a warm Bed, and endanger the catching of Cold, was as mute as a Fiſh, neither could ſhe in reaſon make anſwer to the Diſturber of her Joys, till the Buſineſs ſhe was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout was conſummated: But he, impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient of delay, repeating his Stroaks on
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:153229:61"/> the harmleſs Door, ſhe found her ſelf conſtrain'd to demand who was there, though in Words imperfect as one wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked out of a profound Sleep; and too ſadly knowing the Voice upon reply, ſhe capitulated with him till ſhe might abſcond her Lover, for whom there was no other Refuge but crawling under the Bed: When being ſecured there, ſhe jump'd out, and in great haſt ran to the Door, ſpeaking as ſhe was wont, <hi>Oh my Soul! Oh my deareſt Heart! The moſt welcome Man to me alive.</hi> When in her ſelf ſhe thought, <hi>What envious Devil has brought thee hither at this juncture to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb my early Joys?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Husband thus entred, claſp'd her in his Arms, when the Temptation of her, in a manner, naked Beauties, made him uneaſie till he could enjoy them in a cloſer manner; and immediately throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her into Bed, fell to making himſelf unready, that he might be the more ready, as he thought, to pleaſure her. But ſhe who had already the Satisfaction of a more vigorous and active Inamoret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, knew how to defend her ſelf againſt the weak Aſſaults of an Impotent Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:153229:61"/> as likewiſe to give her Gallant the better opportunity to eſcape, ſaid, <hi>Hold, hold,</hi> (puſhing him back with her Hand) <hi>my dear Heart prithee lets drink a Glaſs of Wine for Joy of thy return, I have Half a Dozen Bottles which were lately ſent me as a Preſent, the beſt you ever taſted; let me entreat you to ſtep down into the Cellar, and fetch up one of them. With all my Heart,</hi> (reply'd he) being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd he might do any piece of Service to oblige her: And re-putting on thoſe Garments he had already diveſted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of, he began to ſearch for his Shoes which he had careleſly drop'd ſo, that one of them was tumbl'd under the Bed; for which he no ſooner began to grope, but out ſhe leap'd; and whilſt her abſconded Lover lay in a quivering Condition for fear of a Diſcovery, and pretending to be angry for his ſo long ſtanding in the Cold bare-footed, ſnatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Candle out of his Hand, ſaying, <hi>Is it poſſible, Husband, you ſhould be thus long looking for your Shoe, and not find it: Come, you ſhall ſtand no longer on the cold Boards, I'll rather ſuffer than you.</hi> And thereupon ſearched for it where ſhe knew
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:153229:62"/> it was not, to avert the Light; and when he commanded her to go to Bed, unleſs ſhe meant to be acceſſary to her own Death, in expoſing her tender Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to the nipping Seaſon, running a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Bed-ſtead, as unawares, ſhe let the Candle drop, which by its fall was extinguiſhed; and whilſt her dear Husband was groping for it, ſhe gave her Gallant the hint, by ſoftly pulling him by the Foot, that this was his only time to eſcape. Whereupon, poudered with Dirt and Feathers, out he crept, and ſneaked down Stairs like a Dog that had loſt his Tail: But not ſo ſilently, but I, who lay perdue, ſuppoſing him to be my falſe Spark, bolted out upon him; and ſiezing the Lappet of his Shirt, he would have cryed out, as taking me for ſome Ghoſt ſent to puniſh him for his Evils, had not fear of Diſcovery over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled his other Apprehenſions; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I ſoon made him underſtand I was not as yet a damned Spirit, by ſaying in a ſoft, though angry Tone,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oh Sir, have I caught you! Are theſe the Products of your Oaths and Promiſes! Can the Current of your ſo often avowed</hi>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:153229:62"/> 
                  <hi>Love ſo ſoon run in another Channel? Baſe perjur'd Man! ſo quickly to relinquiſh her, over whoſe Affections your Subtilty has gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo entire a Conqueſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He thought at firſt, his Wife had ſiez'd him, and began to excuſe himſelf, and beg Pardon in the moſt humble and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching manner; but I continuing to reproach him with Infidelity for his Maiden Obligation, and giving me ſo unexpected a Diſappointment in the heighth of my Expectations. He upon this, knowing my Voice, and finding what I drove at, diſperſed his Fears, and made me believe he had an inkling of our Intriegue, and had left his Bed at ſo unſeaſonable a time, when muttering ſome Threats between his Teeth, he flung from me, whilſt I remained in much ſurprize and confuſion, as greatly aſtoniſhed and confounded at this dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Misfortune, but re-collecting ſoon my fading Spirits, I went to Bed, though I ſlept but little for Ruminating on what had paſt in theſe unlucky Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>My Maſter, it ſeems, went not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to his Wife's Bed, but to my
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:153229:63"/> Spark's Chamber, where rapping and calling Twice or Thrice at the Door, he put him into dreadful Apprehenſions that all was diſcovered; ſo that had not the iron Barrs prevented, he had ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd his Neck, by leaping out of his Window, to eſcape the heavy Revenge he expected to fall on him. However, at laſt venturing to open the Door, with a Reſolution to make an humble Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and beg Pardon on his Knees, his Reſolves were changed, when by the light of the Moon he perceiv'd his Maſter pale, and ſhivering like a Midnight-Ghoſt, all beſmeared with Duſt and ſtuck round with Feathers, only deſiring he would give him immediately one of his clean Shirts; and hinting to him that he had been upon the Diſcovery of his Haunts that Night, he left him far more compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ſatisfied than before, and ſo paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to his Wife's Chamber, who was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain fallen aſleep and dreaming of the pleaſant Paſtime that had befallen her by ſo ſtrange an Adventure; yet waking, diſſembled at this time the knowledge of his Abſence.</p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:153229:63"/>
               <p>My Diſappointment, and the Affront, I conceived with Indignation to be ſo deluded, made me yet reſtleſs, and in the Morning I upbraided my faithleſs A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriſt with many Reproaches. He bluſhed, but hid nothing from me, only begged my Pardon, ſince it was by Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, and conſequently, as it fell out, not to be avoided; but for the future he would be more wary and conſtant:—But finding, though I allow'd him that Freedom he expected very frequently, I watched him ſo narrowly, that the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Intriegues he had in ſecret noctur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and diurnal Correſpondences held with my Miſtreſs, 'ſcaped not my Knowledge; and the Day appointed coming, he ſhuffling and making fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Delays and Demurrs about our Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, I was reſolved at one bold Blow to ſtrike home; and accordingly, having made my Spark fluſtered one Night, and over-dozed him with Love-Poſſet, leaving him as faſt as a Church, I ſtept into his Chamber with the Keys I had taken out of his Pocket, rifled his Trunks, and found the Diamond-Ring, and other known Marks of my Miſtreſs's
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:153229:64"/> Favour, which ſhe had beſtowed on him for ſecret Service, and returned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed. Next Morning being up early, and appearing Melancholy, and much diſturbed, my Maſter obſerved it, and preſſed me to tell him the Reaſon. I ſeemed averſe to comply with his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, which made him the earneſter in his Enquiry. After a while, fetching a deep Sigh or two, with ſome ſeeming reluctancy, I drew the Ring and other Tokens, that were no Strangers to him, out of my Pocket, and letting fall ſome Tears, told him, How my Miſtreſs had not only wronged him but me, in too prodigally diſpenſing her Favours to his Man, who had before promiſed me Marriage: But ſince his ſtolen Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with my Miſtreſs, he, contrary to his Vows and Promiſes, had declined it, if not abſolutely renounced me. My Maſter ſeemed at firſt difficult to believe this, never having obſerved any thing but a modeſt, humble, and vertuous Carriage in his Wife.</p>
               <p>Seeing him pauſe, and unreſolved, I concluded it now time to go thorough with it, and ſaid, <hi>Sir, If you will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:153229:64"/> theſe Viſible Marks of the Injury done you, do but feign an Excuſe to be Abroad this Morning, and I will deliver the Adulterers into your Hands, as ſecurely taken, as</hi> Mars <hi>and</hi> Venus <hi>were in</hi> Vulcan<hi>'s Wyre-Net, inviſibly ſpread to intrap thoſe luſtful Deities.</hi> To this he gave very attentive ear, burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the while with Anger and Fury, his Eyes, as it were, ſparkling Fire; yet a little compoſing his Mind, he thanked me for the Care I had for his Reputation, and promis'd to be rul'd by my Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, in diſcovering the Diſhonour put upon him: and ſo going up, and taking a diſſembl'd loving leave of his Wife, feigned Buſineſs Abroad till Three in the Afternoon, and ſhould not be at Home till Dinner. She took no great Notice of what he ſaid, but gave him a Kiſs, and ſo they parted. My Maſter being gone out, as my falſe Spark ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, he ſneak'd up Stairs, and crept into my Miſtreſs's Chamber; where, by his ſtay, I plainly perceiv'd he was not unwelcome.</p>
               <p>Having them thus in a Trap, I ran to the Place where I knew I ſhould find him, to inform him how it was. With
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:153229:65"/> the News, Anger and Revenge added Speed to his Feet; and forcing open the Door, found them in the ſame Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture he had been with his Part'ner's Wife a little before. Impatient of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, he dragg'd his Man out by the Heels, letting his Head and Buttocks come thump againſt the Ground, beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and kicking him at a moſt miſerable rate, whil'ſt he lay crying-out ſometimes <hi>Mercy!</hi> and ſometimes <hi>Murther!</hi> His Wife, in the mean time, fearing the Death of her Minion, leap'd out of Bed, and taking hold on her Husband, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated him to forbear; And ſince (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd ſhe) you have been as guilty as we, in doing the like with Madam <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norea;</hi> for which Diſhonour to my Bed, I was reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lved to take this Revenge, though, at firſt, unwittingly; it will be Diſcretion in you to be ſecret, leſt you not only publiſh, unadviſedly, your Shame, but ruine your Fortune. Upon this Diſcovery, he ſuppos'd his Wife had been a Witch, ſtanding confounded and amaz'd in himſelf, to conſider how otherwiſe ſuch a Secret ſhould come to her Knowledge; and (to be brief)
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:153229:65"/> whilſt he a little ſuſpended his Fury, my Spark crawl'd from under his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciful Clutches, on all Four; and getting to the Stair-head, made, for haſte, but one leap to the bottom, and tumbl'd Head over Heels down the other, and ran out of Doors, with a Reſolution of never returning; and indeed, I heard afterwards, in the Terror and Fright he was in, going on board a Ship juſt ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſail out of the Port, he was, within Three Leagues of Land, Caſt-away upon a Rock; and ſo, at laſt, all his fiery Love to my Miſtreſs and me, more or leſs, was quenched in the Ocean.</p>
               <p>Upon his Departure, having the Keys I had taken out of his Pockets, I rifled the Caſh, took out Five hundred Florins, beſides other Things of Value that had been laid for conſiderable Summs, and in the Evening hid them in a Wood that ſtood about Four Furlongs from the City, and ſo return'd undiſcover'd; when I found, my Maſter, after her humble Submiſſion, had taken my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, as well as he could digeſt the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front, into Favour again. But this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge ſatisfy'd me not for the loſs of my
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:153229:66"/> Spark; for whoſe laſt Diſaſter, I could not, on ſecond Thoughts, refrain ſhedding ſome Tears; and therefore reſolv'd, the Miſchief I had begun, ſhould go further. Nor left I off, till in the ſame manner my Maſter had taken his Man with my Miſtreſs, himſelf was caught by Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior <hi>Elnorea</hi> in his Wife's Arms; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the injur'd Husband did not roughly uſe him at that time, only rant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at a diſtracted rate, as being too weak to grapple with him, he grew diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented, and took a worſer Revenge, by Confeſſing a Judgment; which turn'd out my Maſter and Miſtreſs to ſhift again in the wide World. The Creditors, upon Notice of what had happen'd, drawing off the Overplus Effects ſo haſtily, that my Maſter found it in vain to ſtand the Brunt; and ſo ſlipping what he could conveniently, ſtood away with his whole Family to the <hi>West-Indies:</hi> and what became of them there, I am ignorant of; yet heard, That his injur'd Part'ner, ſoon after, ſeeing what he had done, to the loſs of his Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Credit in the World, ran di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted, and died in a Raving Fit, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:153229:66"/> againſt his Wife's Diſloyalty, as the Cauſe of all his Misfortune, and the only Croſs-wind that had Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wreck'd his Felicity.</p>
               <p>Being thus, as I may ſay, Disbanded by the Families Going-off in ſuch Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order and Diſtraction; yet having Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure enough to ſupport me till I could find out other Quarters, I took me very ſumptuous Lodgings; where I became acquainted with one <hi>Flavius Dumaine,</hi> a Brisk Young-Man; whom I ſo much doated on, that I conſented to a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage with him, though he was no more than a Blade of Fortune. He, in a little time, ſpent all my ill-gotten Wealth; and running much in Debt, we were oblig'd to bid adieu to <hi>Florence;</hi> and in our Travels, fell into the Hands of theſe Thieves; againſt whom fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing valiantly in my Defence, rather than his own, he was unfortunately ſlain, and I made a Priſoner. They, at firſt, uſed me very roughly, as is their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to all they take Captive, of which they have now divers in ſeveral adjacent Dungeons, in hopes of Ranſoms for the Men; or training them up, by a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſive
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:153229:67"/> Conſent, in their Gang: And as for the Women, by Threats and fair Means, they ſtrive to bring 'em to a Compliance to their Luſts; which I, by the Service I do them, have hitherto avoided; as alſo this Fair Lady, to whoſe Chaſtity our Captain lays ſtrong Siege, by reaſon ſhe proteſts to kill her ſelf, if he violates it.; ſo that in hopes to bring her to a better Temper of Mind, he has not hitherto uſed any Force, as knowing a Conſtrain'd Enjoyment, in Sullenneſs and Tears, can yield him but an Imperfect Pleaſure. At this, the Fair Stranger held down her Head, and wept. And ſo our Diſcourſe, at this time, breaking off, by the coming in of a petty Captain, with a conſiderable Booty taken from Merchants, and other Travellers, we retir'd to the Inner-Places: the Lady, through Fear and Baſhfulneſs; our Houſe-keeper, about her Domeſtick-Affairs, the better to keep up a fair Correſpondence with her new Maſter; and I, to avoid any Suſpicion of my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of Eſcape.</p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:153229:67"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>So different Ends did move a different Thought,</l>
                  <l>Which my deep Projects to one Center brought,</l>
                  <l>And Trapt the Villains who us first had Caught.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>He hears the Complaint of the Beautiful Captive in the Thieves Den; with her Love-ſtory, and how ſhe came thither: Which ſo moved him to Compaſſion and Admiration, that he reſolves to attempt, by one means or other, to make his Eſcape, that he might work her Deliverance.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>PErceiving this Fair Stranger ſigh, and often let fall Tears, I took the firſt Opportunity to entreat the Favour of a Relation, who ſhe was, and how ſhe unfortunately came into this miſerable Place? At firſt, Grief ſtopt the Paſſage of her Language, that ſhe could make me no Reply: but I more earneſtly
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:153229:68"/> preſſing it, and promiſing, if Heave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> favour'd my Deſigns, to be inſtrumenta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in her Delivery from ſo horrible a Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, and the Danger ſhe was in among ſuch wicked and unmerciful Aſſociates, or rather Tyrants, hourly threatning he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with the loſs of her Chaſtity, if not o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Life; upon this ſhe looked on me with Eyes expreſſing her inward Languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Sorrow; then taking me by the Hand, and often whiſpering me to ſit down by her, on a Bench of Earth, covered with dry Turff, letting fall ſome Tears, ſhe ſaid, Ah, Stranger! may I truſt thee with the Secrets of my Grief? Is there any Fidelity to be found in ſuch a Place of Horror, where I ſee my ſelf ſurrounded with nothing but my mortal Enemies? Could I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve thou wouldſt lock up my Woes in ſilence, and any way befriend me, I would moſt willingly do it. Theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions concluding with a Sigh, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd ſhe took me to be one of the Gang. But I preſently undeceiv'd her, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring how I fell into their Hands, and how earneſtly I deſir'd to be rid of their Company. This made her a little clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>up,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:153229:68"/> and the Clouds of Sorrow that eclipſed her Beauty, began to paſs away, and leave the Heaven of her lovely Face in a kind of Serenity; when making me ſwear to Secrecy, ſhe thus began:</p>
               <p>I am called (ſaid ſhe) <hi>Lucindar,</hi> a Native of <hi>Pavia,</hi> though now my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a rich Merchant, lives at <hi>Naples,</hi> on the Point of the Port; his Name <hi>Paulus Urbinus,</hi> of no mean Family in this Countrey, when I was Fourteen Years of Age, going to be a Spectator of ſome Juſts, and other Paſtimes ordain'd in Honour and for the Entertainment of our Viceroy on his Wedding-Day, being marry'd to the Beautiful <hi>Alfrida Mendoza,</hi> Daughter to the Great Duke of <hi>Tuſcany,</hi> I caſt my Eyes, among the reſt, on one of the Youths that maintain'd thoſe Juſts, whoſe Courage and Bravery ſurpaſs'd all the reſt, overthrowing all that came be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, Horſe and Man tumbling and rouling on the Ground together confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly where-e'er he directed his Launce, ſo that the Shouts and Applauſe of the Field were all on his Side, till at laſt
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:153229:69"/> none durſt any more encounter him. Upon which, he retired out of the Liſts, to the ſide of the Stage, where my ſelf, and a great many Ladies of Quality, were ſeated, as Spectators; and taking off his Silver Helmet, flowing with a Plume of White Feathers, he, in a cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous manner, bowed himſelf to the Bow of his Saddle. I no ſooner beheld his lovely Face, and he, as I perceiv'd, had accidentally ſingl'd me out, and fix'd his Eyes on mine, but we gazed one at another, without either of us being able, for a good while, to obſerve any other Objects: I muſt confeſs, with Bluſhes, that I was ſo ſmitten at that firſt Sight, that I am aſhamed of my Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and beg Pardon of my Sex, that I could reſiſt the powerful Arrows of the God of Love no longer: I ſtruggl'd, indeed, againſt my Paſſion, and call'd in my Reaſon to my Aſſiſtance, but all would not do. He was likewiſe as reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and uneaſie as my ſelf; and giving his Armour to his Page, appear'd yet more Gallant and Charming in his Coat, embroider'd o'er with Golden Lillies, and Silver Stars; he left not ſight of me, till <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:153229:69"/> To be brief, we met often, and his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits commanding my Love, I delayed not to give him all the Aſſurance of my Love and Affection he required; which never extended the Bounds of Modeſty. I found him to be a Younger Brother to a Noble Family in <hi>Corduba</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> and gave him leave to make known to my Father the Pretenſions he made to me: but he being of a covetous Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and deſigning to match me to one Richer, and well ſettled in the City of <hi>Naples,</hi> received his Propoſals ſo coldly, that utterly deſpairing to gain his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, I reſolved for once to be diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, which Fear has brought this Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon me, promiſing to meet him one Evening in the Grove, and wholly reſign my ſelf to his Care, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of his Love. As I was paſſing a Road about Two Fields from it, I was ſurprized by Four Horſemen with Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zors on, one of them alighting, ſet me up by Force before another of them, and ſtopping my Mouth to ſtop the Cries I began to make, brought me to this accurſed Place, but by what Ways I know not; for through the Fright I
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:153229:70"/> fell in a ſwoon, out of which I recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not, till ſafe houſed. What the brave <hi>Lyſander</hi>'s Thoughts are for my Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and unwillingly diſappointing him, or how great the Grief of my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents for my Abſence, I know not; but ſure I am their Tears and Sorrows ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in one Channel, cannot exceed mine, who am, to add more Affliction, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted here by a Love I abhor.</p>
               <p>She ended here, and a Shower of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Drops, like young Diamonds in their Infant Dew, fell from her fair Eyes; which made mine overflow for Company. I, as melancholly as I was my ſelf, comforted her in the beſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner I could, promiſing preſently to put in practice at the hazard of my Life, ſomething that might contribute to hers, as well as my own Deliverance.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Pitying ſuch Innocence and Beauty, I</l>
                  <l>The utmoſt of my Skill reſolv'd to try,</l>
                  <l>Eith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r to ſet her Free, or in attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, dye.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:153229:70"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How, after having conſidered many ways to eſcape, he mounted the Smoak-Loft, or Chimney, cut in the Rock; where hiding himſelf to eſcape in the night, by the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den laying on of Fire, he was almoſt ſcorched to Death; and what means he uſed to prevent it; the Thieves Opinions thereupon. How he got free, and eſcaped a Party of Thieves, by falling into a Quarry, and finding <hi>Lyſander</hi> the Fair Stranger's Love, after he had heard his Lamentation, he diſcovered the joyful News to him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>NIght now approaching, our wicked Maſters began to flock home in ſmall Parties, few of them empty-hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and many Diſcourſes paſſed between them of the Buſineſs of that day, and what they deſigned the next; but I little minded the Particulars, by reaſon I had more weighty Matters, <hi>viz.</hi> to conſider my Eſcape. I had obſerved the Door to be narrowly watched and guarded by
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:153229:71"/> two Grim Fellows, in the nature of Porters; I thought ſometimes to bride them; for I had ſtill ſome Gold in the Collar of my Shirt: but thinking if they ſhould take my Money, they might however deliver me up to the Tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; for I took them to be People of no Faith nor Conſcience, and then I ſhould not only be narrowly watched, but my Condition much worſe. At laſt I caſt my Eye upon the little Smoak-Loft, which was a Place cut through the Rock, among a great many thick Trees, and it then ſtrongly came into my mind, that that was the way alotted by Providence for me to eſcape out of the Clutches of theſe Wicked Ones; and ſo bent I was upon a Tryal, that I was impatient till I had put it in practice. I made my Eyes very diligent Centinels to obſerve when every Bodies back was turned on me, and ſneaking into the corner, ſoon by the help of one of the Crutches, or forked Sticks, by whoſe help the Spits were turned, aſcended, as by a Ladder, till I was out of ſight: I found then a hollow Cavity made by the mouldering away of the Rock, through the Heat of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:153229:71"/> the Fire, and in this I ſtood up like an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage in a Cell or Shrine, to conſider how I might in the ſureſt manner take my next aſcending Steps, for fear of falling or prevent Diſcovery, by tumbling down the looſe Stones, I tryed divers that were within reach to find their faſtneſs, the Earth being mouldered away between many of them, ſo that they hung by Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ometry, like the Ruines of an old Town long ſince demoliſhed by War: whilſt I was doing this, the day having been ſomewhat rainy, a great Bundle of Wood was thrown on under me, to dry my New Maſters, which firſt ſent up a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Smoke, which in a manner turned me into Bacon: but that, though very troubleſome, was not ſo intollerable as the Heat that ſeconded it, when the Few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el began to blaze. In this miſerable ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king I knew not well what to do, fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as the Flame aſcended, I ſhould now be ſacrificed to <hi>Molock;</hi> ſometimes I thought to deſcend, and put off my being there with a Pretence I only did it in a Frollick; but knowing among ſuch Villains I ſhould gain little Credit as to being believed, whatever ſpecious
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:153229:72"/> Pretences I ſuggeſted to palliate my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Eſcape, and therefore upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thoughts, I reſolved to ſtand it, though I ſuffered Martyrdom.</p>
               <p>I bethought my ſelf in ſuch a Confla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gration, an Engine was neceſſary, and therefore pulled the little Spout I had, out of my Breeches, and as I ſaw op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, played it as long as the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the Ciſtern would ſupply it, which ſomewhat lowered the proud Curls of the aſpiring Flame: I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they perceived it or no, but imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned they did, <q rend="inline">'For (ſays one of them) it rains very terribly abroad, and our Companions will be wringing wret when they arrive:'</q> yet conſtruing it to the beſt, I concluded in wet Weather part of the Showers were wont to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend there: but now my Ciſtern being dry, the Flame got head again, and put me into new Perplexities; I then begun to beat, and blow down the Smoke with my Hands and Breath, inſomuch that it clouded their Cave, and made them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move further; when to my great ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction I heard one ſay, <q rend="inline">'Take off the Fire, the Wind is turned to the South, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:153229:72"/> by the ſmoaking of the Chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or we ſhall be ſmothered.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The unconſumed Fuel and Brands<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ends, were hereupon immediately taken off and raked away, ſo that my firey Tryal by this means was over; and now all Sooty and Smoak-dryed, having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a little Breath, I attempted my climb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing buſineſs, and ſoon got to the top, ſo that I could peep into the open Air: But here another Difficulty ſtartl'd me; for though I could get my Head out, my Shoulders would not follow: I however puſhed hard forward with all my Strength; but finding I was like the Fellow in the little end of the Horn, I knew not what to think of it: I trembled for fear, and wept for anger, and was almoſt at my Wits end to be ſo near a happy De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, and yet not procure it, but return into worſe Miſery then ever; therefore, <hi>Sampſon-</hi>like, redoubling my Strength, by a happy Providence the Stones that obſtructed me, tumbl'd away, and out I leaped with more Joy than <hi>Drake</hi> when he firſt diſcovered the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Plate-Fleet.</p>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:153229:73"/>
               <p>Being now at Liberty, though in a a Place of horrid Shade and Gloomyneſs, (the Eſcape from one Danger, as is uſual, made the other leſs terrible) I crept through the quilts of Buſhes and Briars, without accuſing them for their ſharp Incivilities of ſcratching and renting my Fleſh and Garments, till I ſuppoſed I was got about Two Furlongs; and there I ventur'd, quite tired and out of breath, to reſt me a while, when immediately my ears were ſaluted with the barking of Foxes and the howling of Wolves, ſo that I fancy'd now I was in the caſe of <hi>Aeſop</hi>'s Hart, who flying his cruel Hunters, fell into the Mouth of the mercyleſs Lyon, by unadviſed entring his Cave for ſhelter. I reſolved however, ſince I had thus far proceeded, to make the beſt of my way; and ſo puſhing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, within Two Hours after, I came into a narrow way that deſcended on the other ſide of the Mountain, which I deſcended with ſo much precipitation, that not minding my Steps, I tumbl'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a deep Pit, and with the Fall much bruiſed my ſelf: But I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I may call this a Misfortune or a
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:153229:73"/> Providence; for whilſt I lay groaning and ſtrugling to get on my Legs, I heard a great number of Horſemen paſs by me, which by their diſcourſe of Booty and Plunder, I concluded to be ſome of our Out-Party returning to their Den. This, notwithſtanding the Pain I felt, made me lye as ſtill as a Mouſe in a Cheeſe, till I heard all quiet; then I took the boldneſs, by the aſſiſtance of rugged Stones ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the ſides of the Pit, to get on upper Ground once more, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing my Stars that I had, by this unexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Accident, eſcaped falling into their Hands; and ſo trudging on, as Day began to break, I entred upon ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fair and pleaſant Fields, and had the proſpect of ſome little Villages at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which put more Life and Spirit into me. Towards the neareſt of theſe I made as faſt as my tired Legs would carry me, in hopes of ſome Refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but by the way aſcending a little Hill, I perceiv'd on my Right Hand, under a little Tuft of Trees, a Cave, and in the Door of it a very comely Perſon ſitting very Melancholy; his Thoughts were ſo employed, that his Eyes were
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:153229:74"/> not at leiſure to mind my Approach till I was pretty near him. I at firſt knew not what to think of it; fear made me ſuggeſt this might be another of the <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditti</hi>'s Dens, which made me edge out of the way, as much as I could, for a large River that run on my Left Hand; at laſt I heard him ſigh aloud and cry out:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O unfortunate</hi> Lyſander! <hi>thus to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken by my viſible Divinity, the faireſt, and as I concluded, the moſt vertuous and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Creature that ever Nature made! Who could have ſuſpected breach of Promiſe from a Mouth that I always before believed ſpoke Oracles, and that nothing but Verity could proceed from thoſe Ruby Lips! But what ſhould be the Occaſion of this new Change or Diſlike I know not. The moſt beautiful</hi> Lucindar <hi>is fled from her</hi> Lyſander, <hi>who adored her next to that Deity who governs the World, and all humane Affairs; and what is more intolerable and tormenting to my diſtracted Mind, perhaps ſhe is fled into the Arms of ſome ſordid Wretch who knows not how to prize and eſteem ſo rare and valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able a Jewel. But why,</hi> (continued he, fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing another deep Sigh) <hi>ſince ſhe flyes from</hi>
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:153229:74"/> 
                  <hi>me with ſuch Neglect and Diſdain, and bears with her my Heart as a Trophy of her Spoil, ſhould I not, after ſuch a Loſs and Diſgrace diſdain to live? Death after ſuch a Loſs is the only welcome Miſtreſs that can eaſe the diſturbed Paſſions of Mind. Welcome then</hi> (ſaid he, ſtarting up in a furious Action and drawing his Sword) <hi>art thou to me.</hi> And here he had died, had I not ſtept in and intreated him to live; for that I had ſo welcome a Reprieve for him, that after he knew from whom I came, he would not deſire to dye.</p>
               <p>My ſudden Intruſion made him frown, and caſt an angry Scarlet o'er his Face, which gave him ſo terrible an Aſpect. though otherwiſe very comely, that I could ſcarce look on him with ſteadfaſt Eyes. He ſeeing me ſtand mute and in amaze, broke ſilence, <hi>Who e'er thou art,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>young Stripling, thou deſerveſt the death thou would'ſt preſerve me from, for preſiming to add more Tortures in deſiring me to retain a loathed Life, than a Thouſand Deaths can give me.</hi>—Seeing him recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, and reſolved to periſh by his own hand, I found it now no time to dally; but ſaid, <hi>Sir, I beg your Pardon for my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſion;
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:153229:75"/> but praiſed be Heaven, I hope its ſeaſonableneſs was directed by a Hand of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence. Did not you</hi> (continued I) <hi>name</hi> Lucindar—<hi>I did</hi> (ſaid he, with up-lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Hands and Eyes) <hi>I named the Fair but Falſe</hi> Lucindar; and thereupon ſome Tears, inſpite of all his Courage, trickled down his manly Cheeks: <hi>She lives</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>lives for</hi> Lyſander <hi>if you be he.</hi> At this ſtarting to me, he claſpt me in his Arms ſo hard; as if in a Convulſive Fit, crying out, <hi>O my good Angel, ſpeak thoſe bleſſed Words again; let thoſe blest Sounds o'er-joy my Ears and Heart; do's</hi> Lucindar <hi>live, and live for me? She do's</hi> (ſaid I:) and thereupon told him all ſhe had told me in the Cave; but in the telling, I perceived him ſo tranſported, that he was ready to ſink under the Exceſs of Joy, which quite overbore all the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards and Dangers of recovering her; his Eyes, by Intermiſſions, ſparkling Fire of Rage, and Tongue Threats of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge againſt he Injurers: then he clapt a Ruby Ring on my Finger, gave me Gold, drew his Horſe out of the Cave where he had ſtood undiſcovered, made me mount behind him, and with a
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:153229:75"/> Whirl-wind's ſpeed, poſted to <hi>Naples,</hi> by well known ways, to engage his Friends and all the Power he could make, for the ſpeedy reſcuing his adored Miſtreſs from thoſe rude Villains Hands; and the more eager he was in it, when I rold him what Danger ſhe was in of being forced to the lawleſs Luſt of the cruel Captain of thoſe Thieves; taking in this, the ſame Meaſures I intended, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving, for the Injury they had done me, in ſeparating me from my Maſter, and the ſcurvy Uſage they ſhewed me after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, to bring thoſe upon them, that ſhould drive out this pernicious Neſt of Hornets with Sword and Fire:</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>That thoſe who plagu'd the World might juſtly feel,</l>
                  <l>For bloody Injuries, Revenging Steel.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:153229:76"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How he conducts <hi>Lyſander</hi> at the Head of a Company of Armed Men, to the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Cave in the Rock. Of the dreadfull Battel fought between them; in which the <hi>Banditti</hi> were utterly deſtroyed; with an Account of the valorous Exploits of <hi>Lyſander;</hi> his Reſcuing the fair <hi>Lucin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar,</hi> and being Married to her at <hi>Naples.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>BEing come to the City of <hi>Naples</hi> about Noon, the Noble <hi>Lyſander</hi> immediately went to the Viceroy's Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, who governs there for the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and making himſelf known to him, told him the Condition of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, imploring immediately to be aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with a convenient Number of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Men, as might utterly root out thoſe Enemies to the Government, and all the civiliz'd Part of Humane Society. To this he hearkened with much Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Concern for the publick Good. Then I was called, and taken into ſtrict Examination, the better to diſcern whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:153229:76"/> my Report was true or feigned: I told them all the Circumſtances attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my firſt falling into the Hands of thoſe Thieves, and Uſage to the Time of my E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape, and luckily for the injured <hi>Lyſander,</hi> declaring each particular with ſuch Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemency and innocent Expreſſions, that I gained Belief. The next thing demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of me was, whether I could diſcover the Place of their Abode: this indeed put me ſomewhat to a ſtand, yet I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collecting my ſelf, told them I believed I could, or give a very near gueſs at it, which with little ſearch might be rectified. Hereupon Two Hundred Men well appointed with Swords and Fire Arms, were ordered to be in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs, and the impatient <hi>Lyſander</hi> joyned to them as many of his Friends as the little time would give him opportunity to do. We took our March as ſecretly as might be, without the Beat of Drum or any Martial Inſtruments of Muſick; ſo that by break of Day, I had guided them to the Foot of the Mountain, and it ſo luckily happened, that their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and the greateſt part of them were then together, it being an appointed
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:153229:77"/> Day for dividing the Booties they had taken: However, ſome of their Out-Scouts diſcovered us, and gave the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm. Upon which, theſe daring Fellows by blowing a Horn, gave the Signal to Arms, and came out and faced our Troops; long it was not, e'er a terrible firing on both ſides enſued, and many Men ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with Horſes, lay weltring in their blood. <hi>Lyſander</hi> enraged or inſpired with Love and Fury, broke through the thickeſt of them, charging through, or beating down all that came before him, in ſuch a dreadfull manner, that they began to give ground, though they fought like Lyons, as knowing this to be their laſt Effort: their Captain ſtormed and bann'd the Skies at a diſmal rate; yet finding himſelf over-matched, in the midſt of War and Fury, he forgot not his Love towards the Fair <hi>Lucindar,</hi> and ordered ſome that nearly attended him to fetch her out of the Cave, that if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible he might eſcape with that precious Prize at leaſt: But immortal Powers, how infinitely did Rage tranſport <hi>Lyſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> when he ſaw his adored Miſtreſs in the hands of thoſe Men, who endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:153229:77"/> to carry her away in ſpite of her Cries and Reſiſtance, and delivering her into the Arms of their Captain, who was retired a little out of the Files of War, well Armed and Mounted, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and bear her off. Certainly all the Words in the World are not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to repreſent his Fury; he was ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimated by that ſight, that all their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were not able to reſiſt him; he flew moſt impetuouſly on them, and turning towards him that with out-ſtretched. Hands was ready to receive her, he brought down his Sword ſo forcibly on his Arms, that they fell both together from his Body to the Ground: His Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions ſeeing him receive that Stroke, and fearing ſuch another, quitted her; but ſcarce had they disburthened them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of that glorious Weight, and he thereby freed from the fear of wounding her by a random Stroke, but with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Blow he took off another's Head, and made it rowl, Cask and all, on the bloody Ground, and after this Execution, breaking in among the reſt that ſtood wavering and conſulting of Flight, like a Tempeſt he overthrew them in
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:153229:78"/> Heaps; ſo that from retreating, they be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>took themſelves to open Flight, and be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing hotly purſued, they entred into a Marſh, full of dryed Reeds, by known ways, about a quarter of a mile from the Mountain; which being incompaſſed and fired on every ſide, moſt of them were burnt or drowned, in attempting to ſwim over a River that bordered on it, and fed it with Water by ſeveral Sluces. The Fight being over, and the Purſuit ended, we returned to the Spoils, which upon ſearch of their Cave, we found to be very great, conſiſting of Gold and Silver Veſſels, Silks, and divers Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice; for this was the general Store-Houſe to which they brought ſuch things as they got by Plunder; and in more cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſearching, we found the Female Houſe-keeper, who for fear, hid her ſelf in a Well, dangling as near the Water as ſhe durſt venture in a Bucket; we drew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> up, and I prevented her further Fears by interceeding for her: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſhe lead us to ſome not yet diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered Apartments, where we found more Treaſure, and delivered divers miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Captives of either Sex, almoſt ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:153229:78"/> and famiſhed to death, and being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ured by her, there was nothing more in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Place than what we had ſeen, we marched off with the Trophies and Spoils of Victory and Revenge.</p>
               <p>It is impoſſible for me to expreſs the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oy and Satisfaction the Two Lovers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eived at their ſo unexpected Meeting; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir Embraces ſpoke the Tranſports of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir Souls in a Dialect above the Power of Rhetorick, or Oratory, to explain. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n fine, having ridded the Country ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ucceſsfully of this Plague that had ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ong infeſted it, we returned to the City <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hrough the thronging Crouds of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>houting People; and the Father of the Fair <hi>Lucinda</hi> underſtanding the Misfortune of his Daughter, and the Merit of her Renowned Deliverer, upon the Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oy's Recommendation, conſented to the Marriage, which was celebrated with great Joy and Triumph, and I was ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſed and highly rewarded for my ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Diſcovery.</p>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:153229:79"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here good Succeſs attends me; but the next</l>
                  <l>Shows me out-trick'd, defeated, robb'd and vext;</l>
                  <l>And, more than ever, leaves <hi>Ragoue</hi> perplext.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How travelling towards <hi>Rome,</hi> and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving various Matters in his way. He is impoſed on in his Inn by a company of Bravo's, and their Trulls. How in the Night, thinking all ſafe, he hears a Cry of Thieves and Murther in his Room: Is whipt, Robb'd, and has other roguiſh Tricks put upon him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Lived ſome time happily in the City of <hi>Naples,</hi> and loath was <hi>Lyſander</hi> to part with me: but being of a Rambling Genius, and now I was abroad, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to Travel, and ſee more of the World, I beggd Leave to depart in ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing new Adventures, and in hopes of
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:153229:79"/> better Luck than had before befell me: <hi>Lyſander</hi> at my Departure beſtowed a Purſe of Gold on me, and the fair <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cindar,</hi> a very rich Jewel; and with much Regret they diſmiſſed me.</p>
               <p>Leaving this City, and having heard how famous <hi>Rome</hi> was for its Antiquity, and its preſent Grandeur, I reſolved to Travel thither. But hearing that the Ways that lead to it, by reaſon of the great reſort of People, and Booties to be met withal, were peſter'd with Thieves and Pillagers, I was reſolved to trudge it partly on Foot, and partly by the Waggon-Coaches, which they call their <hi>Sieges-Volants,</hi> as I found opportunity to meet with in Inns, or on the Road, when moſt weary'd: And ſo providing me a Suit of ordinary Cloaths, the leſs to be ſuſpected, I ſet out on <hi>Monday</hi> in the Morning, having taken Notes of Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions for my neareſt Cut; and in my Paſſage obſerved the Houſes of many no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Families ſtand tottering, decayed, and un-inhabited, by reaſon their Own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Extravagancy had reduc'd them to that Poverty they were not able to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them. When Evening came on, I
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:153229:80"/> went to a pretty handſome Village, and enquired for a Lodging, finding by the reſort in an Inn there, that I ſhould not miſs of ſome conſiderable Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. So that being admitted a Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant at Will, I walked about till Supper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time.</p>
               <p>In the mean while, the Inn-keeper enquired my Name, ſaying it was the cuſtom of the Place that he might give the better Account of his Gueſt, though afterward, to my coſt, I found it was to another purpoſe: For no ſooner was I ſat down, and had called for a Can of <hi>Florence</hi> Wine, and the Servants not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently anſwering, Two Bravo's and a Trull came and placed themſelves at the ſame Table, and bringing Wine with them, drank to me. They had ſeen me before, it ſeems, pull out ſome Money, as cautious as I was to conceal it, and ſo concluded the Reckoning ſafe enough. I continued however ſtill to call the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant; but with a great many Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they aſſured me they were all my Servants: <hi>As we</hi> (continued they) <hi>ſhall teſtifie by our Endeavours to oblige you.</hi> And thereupon cryed, <hi>Ho! Maſter of the</hi>
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:153229:80"/> 
                  <hi>Houſe, make this Gentleman welcome: Set open your Pantry-door and Cupboards, and we'll ſee you well pay'd.</hi> Then one of them fixing his Eyes more intent on me, leap'd over the Table to Embrace me, ſaying, <hi>O Monſieur</hi> Ragoue! <hi>who would have thought to have ſeen you here! Its Ten Years ſince I had the Honour to pay my Reſpects to you.</hi> He ſpoke this in French, as knowing by my Tone I was of that Nation: And whilſt, whether I could call him to mind or not, (for it came not into my Memory that I had ever ſeen him in my Life) he paſſionately cryed out, <hi>O Wretch that I am, I now ſee I am much alter'd ſince you have forgot me.</hi> He being here nonpluſt how to go on, up comes the other, and with as great ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Admiration, ſaid to his Companion, <hi>Is this that Gentleman's Son, whoſe worthy Deeds in Feats of Arms you have ſo often extolled to the Skies? Surely we are very happy we have met thus accidentally with him: He's grown pretty tall, God bleſs him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This kind of Diſcourſe had almoſt confounded me; for by it, one would have gone near to have thought, they
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:153229:81"/> had been born in the ſame Houſe and bred up with me; yet I very ſeriouſly aſſured them, I could not remember I had ever ſeen any of them in my Life. <hi>No!</hi> (ſaid they, as ſtruck with Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) <hi>that is very ſtrange as we ſhould be alter'd ſo much in ſo little a time.</hi> Then I began to ask them ſome Queſtions which I was certain they could not poſitively anſwer: So that their Trull fearing they woud be gravelled, daſhed them aſide with ſaying, <hi>I ſee the Gentleman has forgot you; therefore lay this Diſcourſe aſide till another time, ſince Supper is juſt entring on the Table.</hi> She had no ſooner ſaid ſo, but up they ſtarted, and began to place the Chairs, ſtraining Complements with me to ſit at the upper end, which all my Rhetorick and Refuſals could not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void.</p>
               <p>By this time the Table being covered with Diſhes of a kind of ſtrange Varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, though but very little Meat in them. They fell on with Stomachs like Famine it ſelf; and when they (for though I was hungry I could eat little for gazing on ſuch Gormondizers) had almoſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ured all, in came Three more of the
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:153229:81"/> ſame Tribe, with each of them a lean ſhrivel'd Serving-Man, as I thought them, at their Tails. Theſe taking Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the Bravo's and their Mort, they invited them to ſit down and thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd for more Proviſion, which was as quickly brought up; and ſo they fell on afreſh, and my Hoſt forgot not to ſcore it: For when the Fury of the Buſineſs was over, we found we had, as my Hoſt was pleas'd to ſcore it, Five Chequins of Gold, amounting to Twenty French Crowns to pay. At this they ſtared on each other, and held a profound ſilence, whilſt I was fumbling in my Pocket, in Expectation of the Birth of Mountains; but when they ſaw I only brought forth a Mouſe, <hi>viz.</hi> as much as came to my ſhare, one of them ſtarted up, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted I ſhould be excuſed for my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Sake. But I not willing to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding, as indeed they never intended I ſhould, to ſuch Companions, leaſt for this Civility they ſhould have further ends on me, preſſed them to accept my Dividend, ſaying, If they thought con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, I would pay more at laſt. Their Trull taking the Wink, ſaid, <hi>Come, come,</hi>
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:153229:82"/> 
                  <hi>what need all this ado! Let the Gentleman, if he ſo pleaſes, preſent us with this ſmall Treat, and do you give him a larger at his taking his Farewel in the morning.</hi> I liked not this Propoſal; ſo that at laſt we agreed, I and the two firſt Bravo's, to throw Dice to end the Controverſie, which of us ſhould pay the whole ſhot; you may be ſure it fell to my ſhare; for they ſo managed their Buſineſs, that putting the Change upon me, the Dice they threw with, run all Fives and Sixes, and mine Fives and Fours; which I perceiving, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to detect it, their Mort ſnatched them up, and by the Art of <hi>Hocus Pocus</hi> chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them into Regular ones; ſo that I had the Voice of the whole Board a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, inſomuch that I was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to pay the Reckoning, though the Diſſembling Villains vowed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted they had rather it had fallen to ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of their Lots to have the honour of treating me, with large Promiſes, what great Things they would do the next Morning to make me amends. I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled my Diſcontent as well as I could; and they perceiving I would not engage in Gaming, but counterfeiting Drowſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:153229:82"/> and deſirous to be a Bed, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany broke up, and I was ſhewed to my Lodging. I had, as I thought, a Chamber to my ſelf, but was fatally miſtaken; for what I took for a Wall was only a Curtain that parted it.</p>
               <p>Before I went to Bed, I took care to barrocade the Door with old Trunks, Stools, and Chairs, but never minded what a weak Back I had to my Appart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And ſo going to Bed as ſoon as my Two Inches of Candle were burnt out, I fell aſleep; but was ſoon awaked with a capering up and down the Room, and an Out-cry of Murther and Thieves. Upon this, I leaped out of the Bed, and run to the Door to ſee whether it was faſt or not; and finding nothing remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, I wondred how the noiſe ſhould be in my Room, unleſs the Place was Inchanted: But as I was about to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the Barrocades to run and raiſe the Houſe, I found my ſelf incircl'd with a Horſe-whip, which at every Laſh I thought had cut me in two, and made me roar out as loud as the other had done. And indeed I had greater Cauſe; for I ſince concluded theirs was only in Jeſt,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:153229:83"/> and mine down-right Earneſt; for they were worſe than <hi>Bridewell</hi> ſtrokes, ſtill circling my Waiſt and Shoulders. I flew to my Bed thinking to get under the Cloaths for a Refuge, but found they were taken away; ſo that I had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhelter than to creep under it. In the mean while, ſome body had dung'd juſt in the middle of my Couch, and layed the Cloaths on again: And by this time the Inn-keeper, the better to colour the buſineſs, came thundring at the Door, demanding what the cauſe was of Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour at ſuch an unſeaſonable time of Night. Whereupon I heard one or Two leap out at the Window into a Back-Yard, and the noiſe of the Whip ceaſed: And by this time my Hoſt had jumbled open the Door, or unlocked it with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Key, and was entred with a light, bringing his Oſtler and Tapſter at his Heels; and running haſtily forward, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a huge Two-Handed Fellow, he beat me over and over. I thought now they were come to ſhew me the Italian Trick which I had heard of in my own Country, <hi>viz.</hi> To circumciſe my Jugu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars with a Raſor, or pink my Jacket
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:153229:83"/> with a Ponyard; which put me into a greater Fear than before: after having rowl'd about with me a little while, and pretending to know by my voice who it was, he kindly raiſed me up, and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged my Pardon; ſaying, He took me for one of the Thieves. But I after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards underſtood the Cauſe of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Error was to give theſe Hell-Hounds opportunity to ſee whether the others had made clear Work with my Pockets, or to take the Gleanings. I took this Apology however, in good part, as knowing not how to help it: he then took me by the hand, and lead me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Curtain Partition, where I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expectedly found Two Beds, in one of them was one of the Bravo's and his Mort, whom he called his Wife; and in the t'other the other who had ſupped with me: they lamentably complained of the Stripes they had received. <hi>The Devil take the Rogues</hi> (ſaid they) <hi>they have flea'd our Skins. I had like</hi> (ſaid the firſt that opened his Mouth) <hi>to have catched one of them; he narrowly ſlipt thro' my hands, but I reached his Buttocks with the point of my Ponyard as he was leaping</hi>
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:153229:84"/> 
                  <hi>out at the Window, and gave him a Mark for his Roguery.</hi> Upon this, the Hoſt and his Men promiſing to ſit up and watch the remainder of the Night, weary and much out of order, I got me again to Bed, and preſently fell aſleep, without perceiving the Bedfellow I had gotten. My ſleep was not however ſo ſound, but I often turned from one ſide to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, inſomuch that when I awaked I found my ſelf anointed all over with Pilgrims Salve.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as day appeared, they all came to my Bed-ſide to utter their mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, though diſſembled Complaints; I kept cloſe, and anſwered them but little, deſiring to lye longer, for I had but little ſleep that night: they knew as well as I the cauſe of my Delay, and therefore out of Courteſie, as they ſaid, began to move the Bed-Cloaths to cover me bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; which ſo ſcented the Chamber that they were forced to hold their Noſes, and retire at ſome diſtance. The Hoſt, who knew what was done, immediately came and deſired me to riſe, for that ſome Gentlemen who had travelled all night, were come in weary, and deſired to lye
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:153229:84"/> down to refreſh themſelves a while. I knew not well what Excuſe to make, but feigned to ſwoon away; whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they raiſed me up, and bent my Fing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſo hard, under pretence of recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them, that they pulled two of them out of Joint: at laſt I perceived all was diſcovered, and it could be no longer hid, out I jumpt, and ſtunk 'em to an awful Diſtance. My Hoſt perceiving how finely the Sheets were gilded, tho' I made many Excuſes, began to grum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble like a Dog between two Doors, ſwearing he would have ſatisfaction for the Abuſe of his Linnen: but the Two Bravo's interceeding on my behalf, that ſuch a Misfortune, in ſuch Frights, might happen to the beſt of Gentlemen, he ſeemed to be pacified, and ordered me a Tub of Water to ſweeten my ſelf in, after I had for ſome time lain battling in my Dung; which being placed under the Pump, they pumpt ſo faſt on me, that I was almoſt ſtifl'd. This put me in mind how I had ſerved my Old Maſter, who was here in ſome meaſure revenged. But oh! the miſerableſt Part was yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind; when I came to look for my
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:153229:85"/> Cloaths, they were vaniſhed, together with all my Moneys, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at this, I cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out with a lamentable Voice, I was undone, I had loſt Four hundred Crowns in Gold, beſides Rings and Jewels of as great a value. At this they began to ſtare as if they ſcarcely gave credit to what I ſaid: but I continuing to affirm it, they ſwore in a ſeeming great Rage they would find out the Rogues tho' they went to a Conjurer; and ſo left me in a naked Condition, to the mercy of my Hoſt, I never ſeeing them more; tho' I believe they needed not have conſulted the Devil to know who had robbed me, no more than they might have doubted going to him themſelves, when they dyed.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>But by theſe Tricks perhaps I may gain Wit,</l>
                  <l>T' enable me, Rogues in their kind to fit;</l>
                  <l>He ne'er can Bite well, that was never Bit.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ragoue</hi> go on then, in thy ſwift Career,</l>
                  <l>And make thy Roguery imminent appear,</l>
                  <l>That all may wonder, when thy Pranks they hear.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:153229:85"/>
               <p>Being thus gulled and cheated of all I had, but thoſe Piſtoles I ſowed up in the Collar of my Shirt, I begged to have an old Frock to cover me, which I could not obtain, till they ſee I had ript out ſome Treaſure: at which ſight my Hoſt grinn'd, and applauded my Policy, in making ſome Reſerve in time of Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; though I doubt not but at the ſame time he wiſhed his Comrogues had ſtript me to the Skin, that I might have no place ſuſpected to hide a Silver ſpan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle in: For it is paſt all peradventure, but he came in for the largeſt Snack, and lived moſtly by the practice of ſuch Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine; but being in a ſtrange Place, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilled in the Laws of the Country, and not knowing how to remedy my ſelf, I was obliged to be ſilent, and in haſte to be gone cut of ſo wicked a Houſe; wherefore ſending for a Taylor, he fitted me with ſome ſecond-hand Cloaths, at a moderate Rate; ſo having returned the Frock, and diſpoſed of a Crown for a double-dyed Hat, not worth Twelve pence, with ſome ſmall Expences to the Houſe, I departed with a heavy Heart: when having got ſome Miles diſtant,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:153229:86"/> down I ſate me by a Wood-ſide, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moan my Misfortunes; but finding no boot to ſtay there, up I got, and trudged on my intended Deſign:</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>For being made Fortune's Tennis-Ball, I thought</l>
                  <l>My Way lay beſt, where moſt was to be got</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How going to a Gentleman's Houſe, he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook to lye in a Room where a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Ghoſt was fancy'd to appear; and how perſonating it himſelf, he frighted a whole Table of Gameſters away, and ſwept up the Stakes they left behind for haſte, with which he repleniſhed his Empty Pockets.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>REſolved, if I could help it, to lye no more in a Roguiſh Inn, when Day was near ſpent, I made up to a very fine ancient Building; where at ſome Diſtance my Ears were ſaluted with Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, and merry Songs; which made me
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:153229:86"/> hope for good Entertainmente (it being in thoſe Countries a ſign of good Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeping) I therefore ſet a good Face on it, and went to the door, demanding if the Maſter of the Houſe was within: he thereupon came, as being within hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and asked, What I would have? I told him being a Stranger in thoſe Parts, and having been ill uſed upon taking up Quarters in Publick Houſes, I would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat him to ſpare me a Lodging that Night. He anſwered me mighty civilly, but ſaid, He feared he could not; for it being the Anniverſary of his Wedding-Day, he had divers Friends there, and knew not but moſt of 'em might ſtay all night. I continued to preſs my Suit, and told him ſome of my Misfortunes Seeing me a likely Young Man, he told me he had one Room he knew no body would lye in, which he could well ſpare; but if I accepted that, I might perhaps fall into greater Misfortune than I had yet done, for that it was nightly haunted with a Spirit, ever ſince his Grandfather's Barber, for Love of a Coy Chamber-Maid, had cut his Throat in it, and that the Spirit appeared at uſual times with
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:153229:87"/> Razor in one hand, a Baſon and Light in the other; crying in hoarſe Tone, <hi>Will you be ſhaved?</hi> and ſome that we have ventured, unknown to them, to lye there, have been for refuſing to ſuffer him to ſhave them, thrown violently out of their Beds, and bruiſed at a ſtrange rate.</p>
               <p>I heard very attentively this Relation, but having always a ſtrong Fancy that theſe Reports of Apparitions were only Deluſions and the Fancies of Whimſical Brains, or Men in Drink; I with much obliging Language told him, That if he pleaſed, I would accept of his Proffer, notwithſtanding the dreadful Report he had made, and knew not, but by an Art I had learned, I might lay this poor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed Ghoſt to reſt; that he ſhould be confined to the Lower Shades, and wander about the World no more. At this he appeared altogether yielding, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viting me in, and cauſed me, after we had diſcourſed a little whence I came, and whither I was going, to enter the Parlour, and make merry with the reſt of the Company; and at Supper-time told them for what I came thither, and
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:153229:87"/> what I had undertaken. They all won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that I durſt venture upon it; ſome diſſwaded me from it, as a thing too full of Preſumption, and Danger: ſome again laughed in their Sleeves to think what ſport they ſhould have in the Relation of this Adventure next morning; but they had little Cauſe, as it fell out, though they did ſo. Supper ended, they adjour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into a large old faſhioned Hall, and fell to Cards and Dice.</p>
               <p>Seeing them ſet in, and the Stakes thrown down briskly, a merry Crotchet came in my Head, and retiring, deſired one of the Servants, for that I was weary with long Travel, to ſhow me up to my appointed Lodging: the Fellow, tho' a Luſty Lubber, gave me a Candle, but durſt venture no further than the Stair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot, and there wiſhing me a Good-night, ſtood liſtening a little, and then depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: I ſhut the Door, and expected the frightfull Gobling, but he gave me none of his Company: wherefore leaſt he ſhould be miſſing in the Family, I reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to perſonate him. Thus concluding, I rubbed my Face over with the White of the Wall, to make me repreſent a Ghoſt
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:153229:88"/> the more exactly; then with one of my Garters tying a Sheet with a Knot to place juſt upon my Head like a Shroud, I ſtript me to my Shirt and Drawers, and laid my Cloaths decently on the Bed, the ſooner to whip in after this Exploit: a Razor I had in my Pocket, and to make it look more terrible, I cut my Finger, and bloodied it over; but being at a Loſs for a Baſon, I at laſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the Pewter Chamber-pot, by the glimmering of Candles, and in a Fright, might be taken for it, as well. In this Poſture I waited, till I heard by their noiſe and ratling of Money, the Wine was got into their Crowns; then ſoftly deſcending in the ſame Poſture as the other had been deſcrib'd to appear, I found them ſo buſie at their Game, that I was in a manner at their backs, when one of the Servants that attended, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up, and ſpying me, ſtarted ten Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces back, crying out, <hi>Oh! the Ghoſt! the Ghoſt!</hi> and ſo run out, ſtumbling head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long over the Threſhold; I immediately extending my Piſs-pot, and bloody Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zor, ſeconded him with crying out in a hoarſe and dreadfull Tone, <hi>Will you be</hi>
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:153229:88"/> 
                  <hi>ſhaved?</hi> upon this, they all ſtarted up without any regard to their Money that lay on the Table, and tumbled over each other for haſt, as if they had bid the Devil take the hindmoſt; and happy was he that could tread over another to get before him. I ſtill purſued them in the ſame dreadfull Tone, till I had quite cleared the Hall and adjacent Rooms of every Soul of them; ſome got into the Cellars, others into the Stables and Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, ſculking and hiding themſelves; Fear charming many of them in thoſe Places as in inchanted Caſtles, till Day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light appeared, and baniſhed the Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bears of nightly Fancy.</p>
               <p>I upon this, returned to the Deſerted Spoil, and pretty well lined my Pockets, taking this as a Providence to make up in ſome part, my Loſs at the Inn, and ſo returned to Bed as ſoftly as could be, and putting out my Candle, I ſoon percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved how this Errour came: there was an old doated Poſt in the Room, that looked whitiſh, or ſhining, in the Dark, and the Wind blowing then a Pent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of thin Boards juſt over the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, ſwaying too and fro, made ſuch a
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:153229:89"/> kind of a noiſe, as ſeemed to imitate <hi>Shave;</hi> and no doubt the Drunkenneſs, or Fear, of ſuch as lay there, had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved the dreadful Conſequences of it, by leaping out of Bed, and hitting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt the Bed-Poſts, or tumbling on the Floar. The next morning they were not ſo much vext that the ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Goblin had carried away their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, as for an ill Report, if I ſhould be murthered; for they concluded no leſs, ſeeing the Razor all bloody: but when they ventured to call to me at the Stair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot, and I aſſured them I was not yet dead, (though in a faint Voice, for I had cut off ſome of my Hair, and one ſide of my Beard to make it more paſſable) they rejoyced, and deſired me to leave my Purgatory. I ſoon deſcended, and upon their Requeſts, gave them a very dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Relation, how at firſt refuſing to let him Shave me, he attempted to Cut my Throat; but I ſo guarded it with my Hands, that he only cut my Finger, and having done what they ſaw, paſſed away from me, as I thought, down ſtairs; and returned ſoon after in the ſame Poſture, rattling ſomething in or about his Hands,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:153229:89"/> like Chains. <hi>A Pox</hi> (ſays one of them) <hi>a plaguy Toad of a Ghost; that was our Money he ſtole off the Table then: I have often heard theſe Goblins diſcovered hidden Treaſure for the Advantage of others, but never that they coveted it before. It may be</hi> (ſaid the Maſter of the Houſe, half ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) <hi>ſome of your Fathers owed him for Trimming in his Life-time, and now he came to you for their Quarteridge.</hi> Upon this, they all burſt out a laughing: but I ſomewhat better pleaſed them, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe of the Family, when I told them I heard him mutter as he paſſed out at the Caſement, that his Time of wandring abroad in the World was now expired, and this was the laſt time he ſhould appear; inſomuch that I was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited to ſtay the next night, to ſee if he would be as good as his Word: but fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing when they had better recollected their ſcattered Senſes, they might ſee into the Trick I put upon them, they could o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blige me to no more than to take a Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt with them: and ſo being a little li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral to the Servants, I parted; laughing in my Sleeve to think what ſuch a Fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zy, as a ſuggeſted Fear, though ne'er
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:153229:90"/> ſo groundleſs, can throw Mens Minds and Wit into.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How coming to <hi>Rome,</hi> he fell into the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of ſtroling Players, Fidlers, and Dancing-Maſters; and of a pleaſant Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture that befell; with the downfal of their Cuſtard Supper. Alſo another Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Adventure in the Play-houſe, and how he left them.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>AFter a tedious Travel, without meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with any Adventure worthy of Note, I came to the Suburbs of the <hi>Seven Hill'd City,</hi> and thought it beſt there, for cheapneſs and conveniency, to take up my Quarters without entring the Gates; leaſt coming ſo late a Stranger thither, I might be taken for a Spy, there being an Army of Frenchmen then at <hi>Mantua,</hi> and no good Underſtanding between the Pope and the Crown of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:153229:90"/>
               <p>Long I had not enquired of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that ſold Herbs and Fruit, who had their little Stalls under the City Wall, but they directed me to a pretty com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact Houſe, though of no largeneſs, where I found divers merry Pot-Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions heating their Noſes with good Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, till they looked like the lighted Ends of Charcole: amongſt theſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Topers I ſate me down. (For indeed the low Rooms were but few; the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of this Company, I perceived conſiſted of Stroling Players, Fidlers and Dancing-Maſters; as by their Catches, throwing out Fragments of Old Plays, capering and ſcraping, my Judgment ſoon inform'd me; and as I conjectured, ſo I found it.) Being very needy, as moſt of thoſe kind of Cattle are; they were very ſweet upon me, eſpecially when they knew I was a New-comer: But Experience taught me to be as ſhye of them as an Alderman is of a Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er's Treat, when he ſuſpects it is only a Bait layed to hook him in for a Summ of Money without a Mortgage. However, we drank about ptetty briskly, till one of them tipt me the Wink to ſtep aſide
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:153229:91"/> with him; and what ſhould it tend to, but to tell me he was juſt ſtepping up to Supper, and if I would go with him, I ſhould be welcome. I knew not well what to think on it; but Hunger prompt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me, we ſtole as it were from the reſt. We were no ſooner got into the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and our Victuals not preſently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up, but to divert me the while, he proceeded to act in Geſtures and Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, ſome Fragments of a Tragedy, made upon a Scythian King, who flying through a Forreſt with his Queen, was himſelf, after a ſtout reſiſtance, ſeized on, and got under the Feet of a Bear. It ſeems he had acted this Part, and juſt as the Wench was coming up with a Diſh of Cuſtards which he had ordered for his Supper, the Poetick Rapture took him in the Noddle, and fancying him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the Bear's Clutches, he thus, in a paſſionate and very earneſt Tone, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought his Queen to ſave her ſelf by flight.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>O flye! my Queen, from this devouring Bear;</l>
                  <l>Let it ſuffice, he me alone do's tear:</l>
                  <pb n="167" facs="tcp:153229:91"/>
                  <l>O ſave thy ſelf, the bloody Bear's Jaws flye;</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould'ſt thou, whilſt thou may'ſt eſcape him, dye?</l>
                  <l>O haſt, be gone; or thy Death too, is nigh.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>The Maid being by this time at the ſtair-head, in a great fright concluded, that ſome Bear broke looſe, was got into the Chamber a worrying him, and that it was to her he ſpoke ſo eagerly to ſave her ſelf; leaſt the Beaſt having made but half a Supper of him, ſhe ſhould come in for the Second Courſe to make up his Meal; and thereupon made but one leap down Stairs; yet tumbling Head over Heels at the bottom, beat all the Cuſtards in pieces; and lying with her Coats over her Head, her bare Buttocks and Heels up the ſtairs, ſhe fancyed the Bear would now ſoon have her by the Breech; which made her roar out la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentably for Help.</p>
               <p>Being taken up, all imbrued in, and almoſt blinded with Cuſtard, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of how this Diſaſter came to paſs, <hi>Oh!</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>for the Love of God</hi>
                  <pb n="168" facs="tcp:153229:92"/> 
                  <hi>don't ſtand asking of Queſtions, but Arm, Arm, and run up quickly to the poor Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's reſcue, whom a monſtrous Bear, come from I know not whence, is now tearing in pieces, and eating.</hi> Upon this, though ſomewhat ſtartl'd, they catch'd up what Weapons came firſt to hand, and up ſtairs they run, ruſhing in upon us in a very furious manner, that I knew not what to think ſhould be meaning of it, till they all cryed out in a breath, <hi>Where's this Bear? Where's this Bear, that the Maid ſays was worrying a Man?</hi> The Player as he could be heard, aſſured them it was only a Miſtake of the Maid's, who had heard him perhaps repeating ſuch a Paſſage of a Play, and by her fear ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted it a Reality. This occaſioned much Laughter in the Houſe; but we had the leaſt Cauſe; for by it we had the bad Luck to loſe our Cuſtards, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to take up with a few hard boiled Eggs.</p>
               <p>It growing late, I was conducted to my Lodging, and made all faſt about me; remembring how I had before been ſerved, and indeed ſlept the quietli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt that night, of any I had done ſince my ſetting out.</p>
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:153229:92"/>
               <p>Being up indifferent early in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, I took a turn into the ſpacious Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſpent the time till Dinner, in viewing its Order and Situation, and perceived that of Ancient <hi>Rome,</hi> little but Ruines remained; the City now in queſt conſiſting of New Foundations, for the greateſt part: For the Pope ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the ampleſt Figure there, they all covet to crowd and build near his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace; yet there is ſeveral of the Ancient Monuments remaining; as of <hi>Pompey</hi>'s Theatre; <hi>Trajan</hi>'s Statue on Horſeback; ſome Remains of the Capitol, where the ſtrong Caſtle of St. <hi>Angelo</hi> is founded, and many other things I remark'd, too tedious here to be inſerted; till wearied in ſo large a ſpace, and my Stomach told me it was time to provide for it, home I went, where I found my laſt night's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion Cooking a good Diſh of Fiſh; I deſired to put in with him, and he quickly granted my Requeſt.</p>
               <p>Dinner ended, he asked me if I would not go and ſee their Play that Afternoon. I told him with all my Heart. But I had better have kept away, for I narrowly ſcaped a Mawling. It ſeems this Play
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:153229:93"/> had been Acted before, and very much diſliked; whereupon they had promiſed this day to preſent another: but my New Acquaintance, who was the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer of it, thinking to keep up his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour by retrieving the Diſgrace, upon ſome Alterations, reſolved once more to try its Fortune.</p>
               <p>The Curtain being drawn, and the Audience in great Expectation; I, as a Friend, had liberty to be on the Stage; when the Firſt Scene beginning with a War, after a Flouriſh of Trumpets, my Friend advanced, compleatly Armed, Back, Breaſt, and Head, as a General, with a Truncheon in his Head: And well it happened he was ſo well fortified; for the People no ſooner perceived they were defeated of their Expectation, but with loud Clamours, not giving him leave to ſpeak, they ſent a Hail-Storm of Cudgels; Brick-bats, Stones, Stools, Benches, and whatever they could get, or tear up, at the poor General, with ſuch Fury, that had he not made, as well as my ſelf, who received part of the Blows, a haſty Retreat, upon the impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Advance made too near the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:153229:93"/> Quarters; 'tis ten to one whether he had been brought off alive or not: and nothing could appeaſe this Popular Fury, which had tore down the Houſe like a Whirlwind, had it laſted Half an hour longer; but a Reſtitution of their Money, and a Promiſe to ſo many of them as would enter their Names, to be admitted <hi>Gratis</hi> to a Play, the next Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: and ſo going home, I pay'd off my Lodging, and took leave of my Company, that I might be the better at leiſure to ſtumble on ſome fortunate Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How he fell into the Company of two beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful young Courteſans, who took him for a Mercer. How in hopes of getting Silks of him, he was highly Entertained at their Lodging; and in a pleaſant Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour enjoyed the Faireſt of them. What after happened on this adventrous Occaſion.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Had heard much of the great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Courteſans, kept here to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:153229:94"/> the Luſts of thoſe that could ſupply them with Money; when having tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd a great part of the morning in viewing the Churches, Pallaces of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Colleges, grown weary, I ſate me down on a Bench before a Mercer's Shop, when immediately up came two of them, (as I perceived by their cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their Faces with Hoods ſo tranſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent that they could ſee and not be ſeen,) and taking me to belong to the Shop, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded whether we had any Silks of the Neweſt Faſhion, I told them No; but a Caravan was expected in a day or two; and if they pleaſed to tell me where I might wait on them, I would bring Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns of ſuch as was very choice. This ſtumbled them a little; but after they had compared Notes together, they ſaid they knew not the Name of the ſtreet, as being New-comers where they lived; but if I would go with them, they could ſhow me. I knew this was a Wheedle, yet reſolved to venture; for now I writ my ſelf Man, and thereupon ſtepping into the Shop to the 'Prentice, as if I had given him charge of the Buſineſs; on the contrary I only asked him for a
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:153229:94"/> ſhamm Name, which he aſſured me he knew not, and ſo came out again to 'Squire my Ladies to their Lodging.</p>
               <p>Being at the Door, I would have taken my Leave; but they cryed, <hi>Nay Sir, but you ſhall walk in, and take a Glaſs of Wine, ſince you have taken this trouble upon you:</hi> for they now took me for no leſs than the Maſter, ſeeing me as I came along bowing to ſome Noble-men and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates we met, as well as wealthy Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, and they in Civility re-ſaluted me; they ſhowed me into a very curious Chamber, hung with Tapeſtry or Wain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcot, gilded in the Saſhes, and hung with variety of Pictures: at length we ſate down at a Table, and drank plentifully as to my part, but they only ſeemingly, as to any purpoſe: then came in a Bas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket of Sweet-meats and Fruits, which being lightly taſted, one of them called for her Lute, which ſhe had no ſooner tuned, but in came skipping a little Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel and a Monkey, dreſſed in Dancers Habit, and about it they went ſo nimbly and exact in their ſteps and turnings, that I had ſeen but few Dancing-Maſters who could out-doe them.</p>
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:153229:95"/>
               <p>By this time the Maid came in, and as I ſuppoſe purpoſely, whiſpering the other; ſhe withdrew, and left me with the other, who after ſome other Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, began to talk very Amorouſly; and underſtanding I was a Batchelor, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frained not to proffer her ſelf as my School-Miſtreſs, to teach me, as ſhe ſaid, a ſoft Love-Leſſon: I was very willing to learn, but feared I ſhould pay too dear for it: I knew ſhe expected as much Silk as would make her a Gown at leaſt, and how to come by it I knew not. At laſt, by her Perſwaſions, I conſented to be her faithful Servant, and ruled by her every way. When being a little hot-headed, that I might not ſeem to be leſs than I had propoſed my ſelf, I in a Bravado drew out moſt of the Money I had got at the Ghoſt Scuffle: this new Allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſweetned her Conceit; and ſo to paſs away the time, we walked together down a Back-ſtairs into a very fair Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, furniſhed and curiouſly ſet out with the moſt delicate Trees and Flowers that <hi>Italy</hi> afforded, and there in one of <hi>Venus's</hi> Bowers, a curious Umbrage conſecrated to Love, I enjoyed the delicate Beauties
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:153229:95"/> of my Charming Nymph; which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated with ſuch Vigour, that ſhe ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed mightily pleaſed with my perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance: but as I thought before, the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of the Song was hopes of Gain.</p>
               <p>After this, ſhe gave me her delicate White Hand, and lead me into a Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queting Houſe, where we were ſaluted with melodious Muſick, and having been entertained with all manner of Delights on Free-coſt, I took my Leave, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to ſend my Rich Preſents. Upon this, away I trudged to the Mercer's, and told him a great Lady (whoſe Name I had learned, and who had a Houſe near the Apartment of theſe Courteſans) had ſent me to deſire him to let his Man carry her ſome of the Richeſt Silks his Shop afforded: To which he conſented, as knowing her, and to the Youth gave them in Charge, which was but newly come to him, and therefore the eaſier to be impoſed on. I lead him through as many By-ſtreets as I could, to loſe his way, and at laſt fixing my Eyes on a Houſe that had a Through-fare, in I went, deſiring him at the Door to deliver his Cargo, that I might ſhow it my Lady;
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:153229:96"/> but inſtead of doing that, I made an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe to the People, after I asked for a ſtrange Name, and they had told me no ſuch Perſon lodged there, that I found my ſelf miſtaken, and deſiring to go thro' the Houſe into the back-ſtreet, I left my young Merchant in the Lurch, to return to his Maſter, after long time having ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected my Return, with a lamentable Story of Sharpers. Having thus gotten what I aimed at, away I went to my Miſtreſſes, who received me very kindly, and there I revelled ſome Days; but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a thorow Search made throughout the City in all ſuſpected Houſes, our Quarters were beat up about Midnight: I happened upon the Alarm, to peep out, and ſpy the Officers, and fearing the Conſequence, put on my Cloaths, went down, and ſtood up cloſe behind the Door, after I had opened it; ſo that when they ruſhed in, out I ſlipt: but upon ſearch the Silks being found in the Houſe, the two Charming <hi>Venus</hi>'s, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the Excuſes they made, were hurried to Priſon, and ſoon after as I heard, had Scarlet Laces fixed on their tender white backs by the Lictor or Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:153229:96"/> Whipper of the City, and forced o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and above to pay a very dear Rate for their ſuppoſed Elemoſinary Finery.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How he robbed the Offering-Box under the Virgin <hi>Mary's</hi> Image; and being diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, by what Trick he eſcaped: his Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guery declared a Miracle by the Cardinal, who before was about to condemn him to the Flames, and he carried in Proceſſion. How he put a Trick upon a Prieſt for his Silver Crucifix and left <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe fear of Diſcovery upon this Prank, made me skulk about in the moſt private Corners; till finding a Ship in the <hi>Tiber,</hi> of my own Country, and bound thither, I ſo ingratiated my ſelf with the Maſter, that he ſuffered me to embark for a Paſſage; yet it was ſome time e'er he ſailed. In the mean while, I ventured in ſearch of Adventures; and perceiving the Door of <hi>Lateran</hi> Church open, in I went and found the People at High Maſs, every one as they entred
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:153229:97"/> caſting Money into a Box that ſtood un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Image of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> which made me itch to be fingering it: when taking my Opportunity, with an old crooked Nail I ſoon picked the Lock, and crammed as much of the Treaſure as I could into my Pockets: but doing it over-haſtily, and dropping ſome Pieces, they made ſuch a gingling on the Marble Pavement, that as Ill Luck would have it, I was diſcovered, ſeized, and dragged before Cardinal <hi>Cibo;</hi> who examining Witneſſes as to the Fact, and finding it plain, exclaimed againſt me by the Titles of Rogue, Raſcal, Sacrilegious Villain, and Heretick, and was juſt about con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning me to the Flames: when fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on my Knees, with up-lifted Hands and Tears in my Eyes, I begged his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minency to hear me; which after much ſtorming he granted, and ſilence being made, in a piteous Tone I told him, That being a vile, wicked Wretch, and brought up a Hugonot, coming to this City in great Diſtreſs and Poverty, I had made my Prayers before the Image of the Bleſſed Virgin to relieve me in my hard Neceſſity; and in conſideration of
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:153229:97"/> that, I would turn Roman Catholick, and ever be her Votary; when all on a ſudden, the Box under her Image flew open, and ſhe pointed with her Finger to the Treaſure, making a dumb ſhew with nodding her Head for me to ſupply my ſelf out of it, which I had thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done, with a reſolve to keep my Vow.</p>
               <p>This being heard with much Patience and Attention, I perceived the furious Cardinal to leſſen his Anger by degrees; when all on a ſudden lifting up his Hands and Eyes, he cryed out <hi>A Miracle! A Miracle!</hi> which all the reſt gabled out aloud, and concluded that none might more properly diſpoſe of that Treaſure than the Virgin to whom it was offered: whereupon I was carried back to the Church in Solemn Proceſſion, and round it on Mens Shoulders in Triumph, whilſt <hi>Ave Maria</hi> was ſung by the Prieſts, and I placed before the High Altar; being afterward diſmiſſed with great Applauſe. Since which, I have conſidered moſt of the Miracles of that Church have their riſe from ſuch Fallacies.</p>
               <p>This Succeſs and Eſcape emboldened me to a greater: For one day going in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:153229:98"/> St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Church, I perceived the Prieſt put a Silver Crucifix, of great value, into a Sepulchre, as their, Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is, upon the Reſurrection; and whilſt they were going round in their Devotion, I, by the Art of <hi>Hocus Pocus,</hi> convey'd it into my Breeches, and ſhuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fl'd among the Croud: So that when he came back to it, crying, <hi>Non eſt hic, ſed ſurrexit,</hi> 
                  <q rend="inline">"He is not here, but is riſen,"</q> he found it ſo indeed; for, after much fumbling, he perceiv'd his graven G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d was gone: And I made as much haſt to get away for fear of a Search. So getting on Board the Ship, ready to Sail, I bid a laſting Farewel to <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>My Store recruited by theſe lucky Hits,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>France</hi> I ſteer'd, to re-imploy my Wits.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:153229:98"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How being Embark'd, a counterfeit Hermit told him a Story, of a pleaſant Trick he put upon the Pope with St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Beard: And coming back to <hi>France,</hi> he hung Two Baſtards in a Basket, about the Neck of the French King's Statue; for which a poor Fryer was hang'd by miſtake, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>ON Board our Ship, I found, among others, a kind of counterfeit Hermit, or Pilgrim, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> had taken that Garb, the better to ſhroud his Rogueries, as he told me many others did; and among other Stories, he told me of the Trick he had put upon Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> XI. <hi>viz.</hi> That coming to <hi>Rome,</hi> and pretending he came from viſiting the Holy Sepulchre at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and all the other Places uſually viſited there by Pilgrims, he deſir'd to be admitted to the Pope's preſence, as he ſaid, for his Benediction or Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, but more truly, in hopes of getting Money out of him, which he uſually gave Pilgrims at their return from that Holy Place; but was told by the Cardinal, That he could not be admitted, unleſs he brought ſome Reliques. He told him, He had ſome at his Hermitage. And ſo taking leave, after rambling about the City, heard an old fat Hoſteſs had been lately hang'd for poiſoning one of her Gueſt, and that ſhe was delivered to the Surgeons to be Anatomiz'd. This put a ſtrange Whim in his Head; which was to get the skinny circle of her merkin Hair; and all which, one of the Surgeons Men, for
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:153229:99"/> half a Duckat help'd him to. This he dry'd and comb'd out, and ſo return'd to the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, telling him he had brought St. <hi>Peter'</hi>s Beard, which he bought, at a great Price, of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Sepulchre. The Cardinal admired at this, and looking earneſtly on it, clapt it on his Muzzle, ſaying, If it was true, it were a Jewel worth a Kingdom; and immediately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduc'd him to His Holineſs, who was in as much Wonder, ſtrictly examining the Truth of it, ſaying, They had his Scull already, but never heard his Beard was preſerved. But he gave them ſuch plauſible Reaſons, as to the Truth of it, that he gained Credit: And the Pope putting it upon his Mouth, as the Cardinal had done, and in a manner worſhipping it, deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded why there was ſo much Hair on the one ſide, and ſo little on the other. O, ſaid our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Pilgrim, <hi>Your Holineſs well knows St.</hi> Peter <hi>was a Jew by Brith, and uſed to play much on the Jews-Harp; ſo that by often rubbing and twanging with his Finger, he rub'd off the Hair on the right ſide of his Face.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This gaining Credit, it was ſet up in the Repoſitory of Rarities, in a Cryſtal Shrine, to be adored by ſuperſtitious Votaries, and a Hundred Duckats were order'd our Pilgrim; who, fearing the Cheat ſhould come to light, had now left the City. Many other Stories we had by the way, which laſted us to <hi>Marſeilles;</hi> where landing, I was overjoy'd to be once more in my own Country after ſo many Perils and Dangers, but in my Travels found it every where very much waſted and impoveriſhed, a great number of People being reduc'd to the
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:153229:99"/> laſt Extremity of Life, by hard Taxes, Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and other Grievances. However, on I trudged through many deſolate Places, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted Seats of the Hugonots, or Proteſtants, who by violent Perſecution, were driven out, or fled almoſt out of the Countrey. Coming to my Father's Houſe, I found he was kill'd in the Wars about half a Year before in <hi>Flanders,</hi> whoſe Death my Mother, poor Soul, had taken ſo grievouſly, that ſhe died, as ſome ſay, of Grief, and as others, of a certain Fire that burnt too hot inwardly. But what troubl'd me moſt, my dear Lady having turn'd her fumbling Lord into the other World, had fooliſhly left the Pleaſures of Life, and bury'd her ſelf alive in a Nunnery, upon notice the Lord I travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with, was murthered in an Inn at <hi>Pavia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being now a free Deniſon of all the World, I reſolved to continue living by my Wit; and our Family by theſe ſad Diſaſters having broke up Houſe-keping, I haunted the Court, and eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly found thoſe that could Pimp beſt had the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Preferments beſtowed on them. I inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my ſelf, by that means, into the Favour of the Court Ladies, as knowing how my Mother had proſpered in that Trade. I ſometimes helpt them to Gallants, or in the Dusk of the Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, lay'd their By-blows at ſuch Noblemens Doors as I conceived they moſt properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to; and reſolving on a Frollick one Evening, looking on every ſide for fear of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, Two thumping Boys that were brought me, neatly plac'd in a Basket, by a Waiting-Woman to a youg Lady, with whom I had ſeen the great <hi>Lewis</hi> very familiar, I tyed it a
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:153229:100"/> about the Neck of his famous Statue, (ſet up in Honour of that Monarch, by Monſieur <hi>de Louis</hi>) with this Diſtich:</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nature, Law, Reaſon, all have plainly ſhow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>That every Father ought to keep his own.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>This being found upon the going about of the Guards, great Enquiry was made, by the King's Order, after him that had preſumed ſo great an Affront, and a Fryer of the Carmelite Order, having preached a little before againſt the Vices of the Court, and glanced much in his Diſcourſe upon this Monarch, he was ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to be the Author or Contriver of it, and ſo was put to the Rack; who in his Tortures confeſſed what he had never done, and was fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hang'd for my Roguery.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>And thus through many Dangers I have run,</l>
                  <l>Play'd roguiſh Pranks, though yet I have not done:</l>
                  <l>Much more's behind, to which I ſtill aſpire,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt for a true <hi>French Rogue</hi> Men me admire,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Phaeton</hi> once, who ſet the World on fire.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:153229:100"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153229:101"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153229:101" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
